.
>> good afternoon everybody.
Welcome to the MARCH 25th, 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan chan present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor engardio
and engardio presents
supervisor fielder fielder
present supervisor mahmood
mahmood present supervisor
randleman present mandal men
present supervisor melgar
melgar present supervisor sadr
sadr not present supervisor
cheryl sherrell present
supervisor walton walton not
present MR. PRESIDENT, you have
a quorum.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk could
I have a motion to excused
supervisors sadr and walton
from today's meeting motion by
chen a seconded by mahmud
and without objection, we can
take that without objection.
>> right?
Without objection.
Supervisor sadr and walton are
excused from today's meeting
and then the san francisco
board of supervisors
acknowledges that we are on the
unceded ancestral home homeland
of the to aloni who are the
original inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula as the
indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the committee
shall only have never ceded
lost nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homeland.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors as
elders and relatives of the
romita aloni community and by
affirming their rights as first
peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in reciting the pledge of
allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD,
indivisible with liberty
and justice for all.
And on behalf of the board I
would like to acknowledge the
staff at S.F. Gov tv
and particularly susan innes
who record each of our meetings
and make the transcripts
available to the public online.
MADAM Clerk, do we have any
communication?
>> yes.
Thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance to this meeting
in the board's legislative
chamber room to 52nd floor
within city hall or you MAY
watch the proceeding on as of
govee tv's channel 26 or view
the live stream at w w w dot
S.F. Geo vtv.Org if you have
public comment to submit
in writing you can send it via
email send it to boss at S.F.
Gov.Org or use the postal
service.
Just address the envelope to
the san francisco board of
supervisors the number one DR.
Carlton be good place city hall
room 244 san francisco,
california 94102 to make a
reasonable accommodation
request under the americans
with disabilities act or to
request language assistance,
contact the clerk's office at
least two business days
in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
And finally, MR. PRESIDENT
and members through a previous
arrangement we will have an ada
accommodation request to
provide public statements as
the first speaker during public
comment this afternoon.
>> thank you.
That concludes my comments.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
>> let's go to our consent
agenda.
Please call items one through
eight items one through eight
are on consent.
>> these items are considered
to be routine.
If a member objects an item MAY
be removed and considered
separately.
>> all right.
I don't see anybody on the
roster so MADAM Clerk, can you
please call the roll on items
one through eight.
Supervisor cheryl cheryl eyes
supervisor chan chan eyes
supervisor chen chennai
supervisor dorsi dorsi I'm
supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
randleman I mandel man I
and supervisor melgar melgar I
there are nine eyes all right
without objection these
ordinances are finally passed
MADAM Clerk please call our
regular agenda unfinished
business item nine item nine
in accordance with section 2961
of article 29 a of the business
and tax regulations code
passage of this ordinance by
the board requires an
affirmative vote of two thirds
of the full membership
otherwise eight votes.
Item nine is an ordinance to
amend the business and tax
regulations code to suspend the
empty homes tax pending a final
decision in eric bain versus
the city and county of san
francisco retroactive to
JANUARY first, 2024 and to
reinstate the tax so that the
tax first applies in the tax
year immediately following the
calendar year of that final
decision.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> can you please call the roll
on item nine?
Supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor chan chan eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and engardio
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder no supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
hi mendelson I and supervisor
melgar melgar I there are eight
eyes and one no with supervisor
fielder voting no the ordinance
is finally passed MADAM Clerk
can you please call item ten
item ten pursuant to charter
section 9.113 subsea this
matter requires a vote of two
thirds or eight votes of all
members of the board to approve
the appropriation ordinance on
final passage today.
>> item ten this is an
ordinance to appropriate
approximately 5 million of
state and federal revenues to
the human services agency to
direct client assistance,
rental subsidies and services
through the calworks housing
support program in fiscal year
2024 through 2025.
>> please call the roll on item
ten supervisor cheryl cheryl
eyes supervisor chan chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and gaudio
and gaudio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor mandolin
hi mendelson I and supervisor
melgar melgar I there are nine
eyes without objection this
ordinance is finally passed
and MADAM Clerk can you please
take us to our new business
item 11 item 11 this is a
resolution to adopt findings
that the marina improvement
and remediation project is
fiscally feasible
and responsible under
administrative code chapter 29.
>> colleagues I think we can
take this item same house, same
call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 12?
Item 12 this is a resolution to
authorize the mayor's office
through the mayor's office of
innovation to accept in-kind
gifts and consulting services
from z.
S associates valued at
approximately 170,000 and adobe
valued at approximately 168,000
for a total value of
approximately 338,000 from
FEBRUARY 26 2025 through JUNE
13th 2025 in connection with
the civic bridge program.
Let's take this item same
house, same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
>> and MADAM Clerk, can you
please please call items 13
and 14 together?
>> items 13 and 14 are to
resolutions pertaining to the
california constitution
appropriations limit pursuant
to the california constitution
article 13 b here are two
resolutions that establish the
appropriations limit for fiscal
year 2024 through 25 for item
13.
>> this is due to the addition
of local nonresidential new
construction and the percent
change in population and within
san francisco metropolitan area
from the previous year for the
purpose of computation of its
appropriations limit at
approximately 11.7 billion
and for item 14 this is
establishes the appropriations
limit for special tax districts
and infrastructure
revitalization and financing
districts and determines other
matters in connection herewith
as to as as as defined herein.
>> all right let's take these
items same house, same call
without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 15 item 15 resolution
to accept payment of delinquent
special taxes in improvement
area number one of the city
special tax district number
2000 and 9-1.
San francisco sustainable
financing from a and b pier one
llc to approve the settlement
agreement and release of claims
and to provide for other
matters as defined herein.
>> let's take this item same
house, same call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 16?
Item 16 resolution to authorize
the issuance and sale of bonds
of the san francisco unified
school district to prescribe
the terms of the sale of a not
to exceed amount of 160 million
of said general obligation
bonds for an election of 2024
series series a authorizing
sale of said general obligation
bonds by negotiated sale and to
approve the form and bond
purchase agreement to approve
the forms of one or more paying
agent agreements and to
authorize the execution of
necessary documents
and certificates pertaining to
such bonds.
>> we'll take this item same
house, same call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 17?
>> item 17 this is a resolution
to determine that the person to
person premise to premise
transfer of a type 21 off sale
general beer wine and distilled
spirits liquor license to
luke's local inc located at 12
66 ninth avenue will serve the
public convenience and to
request that the california
department of alcoholic
beverage control impose a
condition on the issuance of
the license and we can take
this item same house, same
call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 18 item 18.
This is a resolution to urge
the implementation of a
comprehensive and severe drug
market intervention strategy to
address san francisco fentanyl
crisis supervisor mahmud.
>> thank you PRESIDENT
Randleman and thank you
colleagues for the opportunity
to have this resolution
introduced.
First I wanted to thank
PRESIDENT Milliman supervisors
dorsey, cheryl and guardian
sadr for their co-sponsorship
on this resolution.
>> this resolution was created
because the tenderloin where I
represent is home to over 3500
children.
>> yet these youth face
unmanageable circumstances from
witnessing overdoses to as
we've seen in recent reports
being coerced into the drug
trade as well.
>> the fentanyl crisis has
created an unsafe environment
for families and children
and shifted our perception on a
national scale to one that does
not capture the heart and soul
of the city.
>> so many of us in this board
are working to uplift what's
happening on our streets cannot
become the status quo.
And every child in san
francisco deserves a safe
and healthy childhood and every
resident and visitor deserves
to feel safe and welcome in our
city.
>> we've tried different
approaches in this city to
address this crisis and it's
not for a lack of will or
resources but we have to be
honest that there's more
progress that we have to take
and we need new approaches.
The drug market intervention
resolution offers a
comprehensive and community
driven approach from the supply
side of this problem to
dismantling open air drug
markets while creating pathways
for prevention
and intervention.
>> and this was born out of
advocacy from the community
from families at two one turn
to nonprofits two academics who
came to us and said we have to
focus on evidence.
We have to focus on the data
that has been successful
in tackling open air drug
markets across the country.
Organizations like united
players or the families at 2a1
term nonprofits like mission
hiring hall have all said that
they endorse this framework of
a drug market intervention.
And what this resolution is
asking for is that we need
specialists to come in and
guide city departments,
diagnose the situation
and prescribe a roadmap for
implementing a uniquely
tailored solution for our city.
There's three main components
here which is one collaboration
to it across different city
departments because it's not
just sfpd that is involved with
the open air drug market.
It's also department of public
works, department of emergency
management.
So many organizations that have
to be working together
in concert to solve this
problem.
>> it involves deterrence
because as the drug markets are
dismantled, we have to prevent
new ones from emerging.
And so this resolution
prioritizes funding for
community ambassador programs
that provide alternative paths
for first time nonviolent
offenders reducing recidivism
and improving public safety.
Prevention through community
engagement is critical because
we need stronger workforce
and youth development programs
to provide alternatives to the
drug trade that we're seeing
being exposed to our kids.
This could involve investments
in safe passage mentorship
programs, job training to break
the cycle of crime
and addiction.
The impact of the fentanyl
crisis it's not just on the
individuals as we've indicated,
it's on families
and communities and we cannot
allow another generation of san
franciscans to grow up thinking
that the drug trade is their
only option during our public
safety and neighborhood
services committee meeting.
>> I introduced an amendment on
page one lines ten through 15
which have already been
incorporated to clarify on this
objective that enforcement
alone cannot eliminate the drug
market and should be minimized
whenever possible.
This amendment reinforces our
commitment to prioritizing
interagency collaboration,
direct communication
and deterrence over punitive
measures while expanding
pathways to employment
education and rehabilitation
for both nonviolent dealers
and individuals struggling with
addiction.
That clause now reads whereas
dmi focuses the criminal legal
system on disrupting public
markets by acknowledging that
enforcement alone cannot
eliminate the market and should
be minimized whenever possible.
Prioritizing interagency
collaboration between law
enforcement, public health
and social service agencies
replacing enforcement with
direct communication
and deterrence whenever
feasible and providing
nonviolent dealers and users
with pathways to employment,
education, rehabilitation.
I want to thank supervisor
fielder for recommending these
amendments because it follows
the spirit of where my focus is
as well.
>> I'd also today like to
introduce three other non
substantive amendments the
first of which are on page two
lines ten through 18 that will
now read.
Whereas the drug market agency
coordination center launched
in 2023 to enhance coordination
among the san francisco police
department, san francisco
district attorney's office, san
francisco sheriff's department
,department of public works
and the department of emergency
management has made significant
progress including seizure of
over 300 pounds of fentanyl
and more than 2000 felony drug
arrests.
Whereas despite d-max efforts,
enforcement is currently
limited to 3 to 5 days per week
underscoring the need for a
sustained and comprehensive
strategy to disrupt drug
markets and illegal vending
markets and reduce overdoses.
>> and my last amendment will
delete part of the final clause
to now read as further resolved
that the board of supervisors
recommends allocating necessary
resources to fully implemented
dmi strategy including
increasing support for
workforce and youth development
programs and strengthening
community based drug market
disruption initiatives.
I wanted to thank supervisor
chen for these amendments to
help the resolution focus on
the spirit for which it is
intended which is truly around
deterrence and prevention.
This resolution can accordingly
ensure that san francisco's
using every tool available as
the academic co-invented it
describes as a harm reduction
from the supply side to prevent
harm and provide real
opportunities for our most
vulnerable youth.
>> because so many of the
neighborhoods from the
tenderloin to other
neighborhoods in the city
deserve a childhood.
And I'm grateful to my
colleagues for recognizing this
fact and supporting the
residents in any district.
The dmi framework is an
evidence based model that has
worked in cities across the
country.
>> and it's time for san
francisco to take action.
It will take all of us to help
build a safer, healthier future
for all san franciscans.
>> to that effect, I urge my
colleagues to support this
resolution as well.
thank you.
Supervisor mahmud there is a
motion to amend the resolution
before us.
Is there a second for that?
There's a second from
supervisor dorsey
and supervisor fielder I think.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you supervisor mahmud for
bringing this resolution
forward.
>> I'm appreciative of the
conversations we've had.
To be clear, I did not advocate
for specific amendments.
I expressed choose to reserve
mahmud that the dmi strategy
seems promising for holding
dealers accountable.
However, I remain concerned
that an enforcement approach
divorced from metrics related
to public health goals street
conditions will lead to just
more arrests and jailing of
drug users rather than dealers
which ends up being so much
more expensive for our city
budget less consequential for
public drug markets and more
fatal for drug overdoses
in scaling up respite centers
and drug treatment because we
have not adequately scaled up
respite centers and drug
treatment.
We continue to see displacement
effects and increasing fatal
overdoses.
And now new research published
just last week in the journal
of the american medical
association and ising
specifically san francisco data
shows that after a drug seizure
overdose incidents increase
during the next 24 hours
and within 100m of the event.
>> as long as we are unclear on
the metrics along which we are
measuring success and which
initiatives or agencies are
best suited for leading that we
will continue to see
displacement effects
and increased fatal overdoses.
>> we need both enforcement
and treatment if we want street
conditions to improve and I
don't see them as mutually
exclusive.
But I look forward to working
with supervisor mahmud
and everyone on this board on a
more comprehensive drug policy
at the four pillars hearing
I've called for.
>> thank you.
>> supervisor fielder
supervisor chan.
Thank you, PRESIDENT
Mendelsohn.
I came into the space and I to
thinking that I will not be
in support of this resolution
for a couple reasons.
>> first is the reason being
that it seems to oriented on a
strategies that is by one
individual however MAY be very
brilliant and thoughtful.
I also have thought around is
this should we actually be
devoting our resources
and budgets and staffing around
just one person strategy
present it to through academic
setting?
>> I would love for us to
consider it no doubt but not to
center our resources around
this one strategy.
>> and I certainly have a lot
to say about the drop market
agency coordination center
since it develop and establish
on day one both on again the
approach but the resources
and the staffing that we see
which frankly we will see soon
enough in the over staffing,
understaffing and overtime
spending and significant
increase of overtime spending
from our sheriff's department
that is coming at the budget
finance committee in the coming
weeks.
>> all which is to say not only
that I am not in support of the
continuing approach of the
drought market agency
coordination center.
I have a lot more questions
about the the this new approach
simply by one academia.
And so I am not in a position
to say that this is what we
urge the mayor to do at this
time and I most certainly would
like to see a more
comprehensive approach from our
and from our mayor and his
administration.
But I don't know if this is it.
>> so thank you.
Thank you, supervisor chan.
>> so if I am reading the room
correctly I think we can take
the amendment without objection
.
>> okay.
So the the resolution is
amended and then I think we
need to do a roll call on the
amended resolution on item 18
supervisor as amended
supervisor cheryl cheryl I.
Supervisor chan chan no
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsi dorsi I
supervisor engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder.
Fielder no supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
hi randleman I and supervisor
melgar I melgar I there are
seven eyes and two nos with
supervisors chan and fielder
voting no thank you MADAM Clerk
could you please call items 19
through 21 together items 19
through 21 are three mayoral
appointments to these successor
agency commission commonly
known as the commission on
community investment
and infrastructure item 19
approves carolyn ransome scott
and item 20 approves earl
shattuck both terms ending
NOVEMBER 3rd, 2028 and item 21
approves mark miller term
ending NOVEMBER 3rd 2026 can
you call the roll on these
items on items 19 through 21
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and engardio
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
high management I
and supervisor melgar I melgar
I there are nine eyes without
objection these motions are
approved and then I think we
can go to our committee
reports.
>> item 26 item 26 and 27 were
considered by the government
audit and oversight committee
at a regular meeting on
thursday MARCH 20th, 2025
and were forwarded as committee
reports.
>> item 26 is a resolution to
approve the settlement of the
grievance by the international
union of operating engineers
stationary engineers local 39
against the city for
approximately 1 million.
This grievance involves an
employment dispute under the
city's memorandum of
understanding with the union
and I think we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
>> and then can you call item
27 item 27.
>> this is a resolution to
authorize the department of
homelessness and support of
housing to solicit donations
from various private entities
and organizations to support
the expansion of temporary
shelter and other homeless
services to support people
experiencing homelessness
notwithstanding the be hosted
payment ordinance supervisor
fielder thank you PRESIDENT
Colleagues as chair of the
government audit and oversight
committee I am committed to
continued oversight of the
city's practices ensuring that
every city department adheres
to our existing standards.
Recent reports have raised
serious concerns over the
city's contracting process
and we have a duty on the board
to ensure that we put in the
proper measures to avoid any
indications of impropriety
while fundraising to meet our
city's pressing needs for
affordable housing and shelter
beds is undeniably important.
We also have a responsibility
to the residents of san
francisco to ensure that all
city business is conducted with
integrity, transparency
and accountability.
It is important that
philanthropic interests do not
influence or interfere with our
city's policy goals but instead
complement and help us achieve
them.
To that end, I appreciate each
of sage for working with my
staff on amendments for this
item to require reporting back
to the board on how this waiver
is used and to bring it up to
the ethical standards that our
city deserves and respect with
respect to future renewals of
these waivers, I'll be looking
at the reports to see how they
are being used and whether the
city is indeed benefiting from
these waivers.
>> thank you.
Thank you, supervisor fielder.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection the resolutions
adopted.
And MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 28?
Item 28 was considered by the
rules committee at a regular
meeting on monday, MARCH 24th,
2025 and was forwarded as a
committee report pursuant to
the board's rules of order
and amendment to the rules
shall be adopted by the
affirmative vote of two thirds
of or eight votes of the board.
Item 28 is a motion to amend
the board's rules of order to
add a new rule 5.20 2.1 and to
adopt a parental leave policy
for the board of supervisors.
Apologies MADAM Clerk and thank
you and supervisor melgar.
Thank you so much, MR.
PRESIDENT and MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, a couple of years
ago at this board passed
legislation to allow for
parental leave policies
and procedures for all our
boards and commissioners
because before that believe it
or not we didn't have them
in this board of supervisors
didn't have a policy.
>> and I want to take a moment
to congratulate our colleague
who is not here with us today
for having the latest addition
to his family.
A supervisor solder and to
acknowledge that we're all
human beings who have families
and caretaking responsibilities
and it is high time that we
have the rules in our charter
and in our policies that
reflect that as well.
>> thank you.
Supervisor melgar I think that
we can take this item same
house, same call without
objection the motion is
approved.
I guess we could do a minute of
roll call.
MADAM Clerk yes for roll call.
MR. PRESIDENT.
First up to introduce new
business is supervisor cheryl.
>> colleagues today I am
introducing a resolution
recognizing APRIL 2025 as
national sexual assault
awareness and prevention month
in san francisco.
I am deeply grateful that so
many of my colleagues that this
resolution has the support of
so many colleagues on the
board.
We all recognize that sexual
violence impacts people across
all communities regardless of
gender, race or age.
It is a public health crisis
that often begins early in life
and carries devastating long
term consequences.
>> 1 in 9 girls, 1 in 20 boys
will experience sexual assault,
sexual abuse before adulthood.
>> more than 2 million
survivors of rape live
in california today.
These numbers are staggering
but they are not abstract.
They represent people in our
city who live with trauma
and deserve our support.
Our job is to create a city
that listens to survivors,
believes them, ensures access
to care and the justice that
they need.
>> we also have a duty to
invest in prevention, education
and early intervention
especially for young people.
This month is about raising
awareness and recommitting to
action.
I want to express deep, deep
gratitude to the people who
show up every day for survivors
the advocates, counselors,
health care workers, teachers,
case managers, family members
and friends.
They are often the first to
hear the truth the first to
offer care and the ones who
walk with survivors through the
hardest parts of healing.
And I also want to thank the
mayor's office of victims
rights for their continued
leadership in this work.
And I want to recognize the
youth commission for passing
their own resolution
and putting pushing this
conversation forward with
clarity and courage.
My predecessor supervisor
kathryn stephanie championed
this resolution last year
and I'm proud to be able to do
so again today alongside so
many of my colleagues.
>> I'm honored to carry that
work forward and reaffirm the
city's commitment to survivors
and to the people who support
them.
To survivors in san francisco
we see you and we stand with
you.
>> the rest I submit.
>> all right.
Let's go to our 230 special
commendation.
>> yes.
It's now time for the
recognition of commendations
for meritorious service to the
city and county of san
francisco.
>> and I believe we will start
with d seven supervisor miranda
melgar.
>> thank you PRESIDENT Mando
min for this special occasion
to elevate women's history
month and also equal pay day
which is today we will be
recognizing the contributions
of incredible women across the
city.
Under the general theme of
women make it work because
let's face it women are the
backbone of our economy, our
society, our democracy.
And for far too long women's
labor often go unrecognized
and undervalued.
>> right now our federal
government continues its all
out assault on all marginalized
community including women.
It is especially important that
we take these opportunities to
celebrate the achievements of
groups whose contributions are
often unnoticed.
Women, especially women of
color make our society function
.
We are often the default
caregivers the organizers on
top of our day jobs.
but regardless of the job
and responsibilities we have
when something goes wrong, we
are the ones who come in and
fix it.
When the ball gets dropped we
pick it back up.
So today we will celebrate
women in san francisco who make
our city better.
And as we recognize these
wonderful women's achievements
,we should also reaffirm our
commitment to making this world
more supportive for women
and girls.
And with that, let's kick off
our campaign donations.
I have the great pleasure of
honoring someone ideally I
admire as a fierce, powerful
and impactful leader.
>> DR. Zia malala, can you
please come up?
I had the great privilege to
serve with DR. Malala on the
first five commission and later
on the children and families
commission after the merger of
the departments.
DR. Zia malawi is a mother, a
pediatrician and a public
health professional.
>> throughout her career DR.
Malawi has been a champion for
racial justice in medicine,
helping improve health outcomes
for black babies, black mothers
and parents and children of
color for two decades.
She has worked for public
health departments including
the san francisco department of
public health, federally
qualified health centers
and other public agencies
throughout california.
DR. Malala has used this wealth
of experience in her work
leading san francisco's
children and families
commission for the past five
years and co-leads the
california effort which got
medi-cal to cover doula care.
>> in addition to all of this,
she continues to practice
pediatric medicine and see
patients.
Zia and her mother are both
from san francisco.
And DR. Malala grew up mostly
in the western addition and the
fillmore.
She attended john swett
elementary school and went to
lake wilmot high school when
she had a baby.
Oh, she left san francisco
and she went to college in new
york at columbia and then med
school in residency at ucla
when she had a baby.
She came back home because she
wanted him to have some of the
same experiences growing up
that she did.
Upon returning to san
francisco.
She got a job at the bayview
child health center where she
learned to integrate mental
health care into her pediatrics
practice to better support
children who have experienced
trauma in adverse childhood
experiences.
Growing up she attended many
demonstrations in front of this
building, organized meetings
across the city and was raised
by her mother to be politically
engaged.
It did not take long for her to
recognize that good medical
care alone cannot ensure
children of color will be
healthy.
Social justice work
and political advocacy is also
necessary to promote good
health for kids experiencing
racism.
In 2016 she quit her job to
accumulate more student debt
and spent a year getting a
master's in public health at uc
berkeley.
This is also the year she
became the chair of the first
five commission.
>> when she graduated with her
new degree she started working
with the san francisco
department of public health
initially as a contractor but
then as a full time employee
where she was tasked with
finding ways to address the
very troubling outcomes for san
francisco's black mothers.
What they were facing during
pregnancy and birth in 2017 she
started a collective impact
effort that eventually gave
rise to expecting justice a
public health program that uses
systems change and justice
oriented approaches to
dismantling racism and closed
the racial gap in birth
outcomes expecting justice work
to advance access to community
doulas a proven method of
improving birth outcomes
expecting justice also became a
key partner in california's mom
neighbors bill passed in 2021.
This landmark legislation made
full spectrum dual care a
covered medical benefit.
>> at that same year DR.
Mallard won her expecting
justice team launched the
nation's first pregnancy
guaranteed income program the
abundant birth perk project.
This pioneering program
provides pregnant people who
are at risk of birth
disparities with a monthly
income supplement.
Beginning in san francisco, the
abundant birth project provided
mothers with a monthly $1,000
for a year to help mothers
buffer themselves against the
impacts of structural
and historical racism.
>> in 2024 the abundant birth
project expanded across the
state to an additional four
counties and today this
pioneering program has given
out nearly $5 million to 850
pregnant people who are at
highest risk of having
premature births.
Not only is this historic but
it is also being replicated
across the nation spurring a
movement of providing pregnancy
support to be kind
and dignified in the care they
deserve.
>> sadly, there are many
detractors who have also tried
to sabotage this project.
But DR. Malala is undeterred
and continues her fight for
public health programs that
help marginalized families
access necessary care that
support the health of babies
in that they are too often
denied due to the structural
and institutional barriers that
they face.
It is my honor to recognize DR.
Malala into thank you and to
recognize you in the movement
you are leading for the
countless lives you have saved
and for your tireless work to
advance racial justice
in medicine.
Thank you, DR. Malala.
>> thank you so much
supervisors thank you so much
supervisor melgar for this
great honor.
I'm going to put on my glasses
so I can actually read what I
wrote.
>> it feels amazing to have my
contributions recognized in my
hometown and to become part of
a legacy of hard working women
throughout this city.
But even during women's history
month as a pediatrician, I
can't help but think about san
francisco's future about the
babies being born right now
that will become the future
inhabitants of this city.
I'm worried for them
in particular.
I'm worried for our city's
black babies because right now
san francisco has the dubious
distinction of having the
highest black prematurity rate
in the state.
One out of every seven black
babies in san francisco is born
too early.
Nearly twice the rate of san
francisco's white newborns.
Are you wondering how a city
with world class medical
institutions and an annual
budget larger than some states
is producing such poor health
outcomes?
>> the answer is racism.
Too many black families in this
city lack the resources needed
to have healthy pregnancies
and births as a pediatrician.
>> I have too often seen black
parents facing unimaginable
stress because they cannot
afford their basic needs.
As a black mother and a long
time resident I know this city
offers black people so few
opportunities for advancement
and so many opportunities to
experience racial
discrimination.
What would it look like for
this city to truly invest
in its black communities
future?
What would it look like to
truly value this city's tiniest
and most vulnerable residents?
>> it might look something like
the abundant birth project.
When we first imagined the
abundant burge project we
imagined to san francisco where
every parent can expect a
joyful birth where every
newborn can expect safe passage
into the world where the future
is bright because critical
early investments have set the
stage for a thriving society.
The abundant birth project is
on the cutting edge of public
health slicing through
centuries of discrimination.
Meeting our city's challenges
with heart instead of division
and accusation.
And despite the myriad of
barriers we face including
those posed by the city
and county of san francisco
itself, it feels amazing to be
here doing this work.
It feels like we're on the
right side of history.
Supervisors please join us
in this love movement and do
more to protect black birthing
parents and black babies
in this city.
Do more to make sure the money
already being spent to uplift
black birthing parents is used
well.
Do more to make sure we provide
black families with the
tangible support and dignified
treatment they deserve.
>> join me in the forward
facing love centered work of
birth equity and become part of
a future we all want to live
in.
>> thank you.
>> yes.
Yes.
Supervisor chan thank you
PRESIDENT Mandarin colleagues.
It is my pleasure and honor to
recognize the chinese
consolidated women's
association today particularly
to celebrate their 25th
anniversary milestone
and congratulate their elected
PRESIDENT Joanna zheng
and executive board members.
>> you MAY ask.
Knowing that the chinese
consolidated association
and family association has been
a long standing tradition
in chinatown, how come the
women are only just celebrating
their 25th anniversary while
the chinese consolidated women
association was officially
established in 1999 as a family
tropic and charitable
organization to promote unity
and uplift chinese women
through the advancements of
chinese tradition and culture.
But we know for a fact that cwa
was established to pay tribute
to the much delay recognition
of women's contribution in the
chinese american community
and to shed light on the double
repression that chinese women
historically experienced
throughout the history of
chinese migration into the
united states.
Not only did women face the
same level of racial
discrimination and by the U.S.
Government which was
exemplified by laws like the
1975 page act that for bait the
entry of all chinese women
considered obnoxious by U.S.
Consulate chinese women also
had to endure patriarchal
culture values within their own
community like traditional
female responsibility of
caretaking after their children
and oppressive practices like
banded feet.
Despite all that it is
undeniable that women play a
equal role in the social
and economic advancement of the
chinese-american community.
I know many of them took on the
traditional roles of homemaker
and caretakers but also assumed
financial responsibilities for
their families as well as
social obligation to
advancements of the community.
Even today the entirely to ship
at the chinese consolidated
benevolent association is man
it was only until 2022 when the
first woman emerged as to
presiding PRESIDENT Of the
historic organization.
Since its establishment over
175 years ago I would like to
thank I would like to attribute
and thank some of that effort
to seek a particularly in their
empowerment of women leadership
within and outside the chinese
community.
Thank you.
Co-founder doris grover
and 2025 cc w a PRESIDENT
Joanna zheng for joining us
today and thank you for all
your critical work in the
community.
And I'm going to ask them to
come up here on the podium
and join me and they should all
come up and while I have the
mic to is that I want to
recognize MR. Doris MRS. Doris
fong, the widow of late jack
lee fong that she was to a
founding she is a founding
member and has always been a
pillar of our community but
many only know jack lee fong
and don't think much, you know
about the fact that doris
dorothy was really the
foundation of their company
and I want to also recognize
our city hall preservation
commissioner MAY well who is
also joining them today and of
course former aide to assembly
member phil tang, jay chang
and jake wu sorry jay and of
course jan mack who's the board
PRESIDENT For the cic board
director as well as the
PRESIDENT Of our portsmouth
square garage.
>> the floor is yours.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Thank you, supervisor chan my
name is doris grover and I'm
actually I'm speaking on behalf
of our founder and past
PRESIDENT Yvonne lee.
>> she's in hawaii and she say
her heart is with us now I just
want to deliver a message.
>> she wanted me to thank all
the past supervisor
and presence supervisors
and the past mayors and newly
elected mayor honorable daniel
laurie for their support
continued support for 25 years
in the chinese community
and ccw a it's very proud to be
here today and also I'd like to
recognize three of our founding
members of way that's 25 years
ago and the first one is
honorable macy wall and second
is founder and past PRESIDENT
Yvonne lee and the third is
myself, doris grover.
And we also like to recognize
our 20 years of service.
>> dorothy taught dorothy fong
and lily gao our partner both
our past PRESIDENT And they are
here today.
>> so I just she wanted one
wanted to really appreciate
being here today and there's
something very special for the
cwa.
>> we will continue to serve as
chinatown community and the
woman's community.
Thank you very much.
>> I'd like to bring on our
newly installed PRESIDENT
Joanna singh and she's going to
with her leadership we're going
to have another smashing year.
>> hello all respected the
supervisors supervisor connie
chen, thank you very much.
My name is a joy and that's all
the last year co-PRESIDENT
And this year karen the
PRESIDENT Our ccw has a 20 five
year history every year we have
a big charity event.
The most important is in MAY
every year we have selected the
modern mothers celebration
together with women's affairs
at the wall the second day
in JULY and AUGUST that we have
scholarship delivery to san
francisco high school graduates
who are excellent.
>> the students and the go into
the college and the third one
is the outstanding offices the
chinese the celebration every
year we did these are charity
events all donated by our team
members and the directors.
>> we never get the city funds
if there is any grants
in future there is any
opportunity we we apply we want
to make our city better.
Now I'm introduce our team
members then our general
secretary and lee and then I'll
on our board of directors
jeanette the fun just for the
now all introduce the art okay
our honorary our honorary
director doris grover and our
honorary past PRESIDENT Lily
gal our one one of our founders
dorothy fong and the mae award.
They are all 25 years of
history to service our
community and and our
consultant j the woman who is
the somebody for many years
and our legal advisor generally
jan mack van gelder in that
good afternoon my name is jan
mack and I have the honor of
serving as a legal consultant
for cwa.
This is a huge honor because
prior to me there are two legal
consultants were judge lillian
singh and judge julie tang who
as we all know our woman
trailblazers in the aapi legal
community.
It's truly been an honor to be
able to work with such a
wonderful organization.
Many of the founders
and leaders I had the
opportunity of volunteering
with while I was growing up
in san francisco in many
different various capacities
and so I hope that I can
continue to work with this
organization and to continue
the mother's day celebration
and where we get to honor the
sacrifices and contributions of
mothers and parents and also
the outstanding overseas
chinese award where we
recognize the significant
contributions of chinese
americans but perhaps most
importantly I hope I can
continue to work with this
organization on all the
charitable efforts such as the
scholarships that they provide
to youth in san francisco
and the visits that they do to
senior centers throughout san
francisco.
>> so be on behalf of cwa, we
would like to thank supervisor
connie chan for this
recognition and award and we
would like to thank you for
being such an amazing
representative for the chinese
community.
>> thank you.
>> district nine supervisor
jackie fielder that you present
when I started this I thought
as he told us as soon honor as
that a key or provides it when
I'm persona extraordinary I'm
only there inconsolably when I
defend zora the los derechos
humanos cuyo trabajo are
transformable villas
and communities marginalize is
vulnerable but when I was
nicole santa maria is a
dedicated advocate with deep
expertise in healing justice
and anti-violence work.
Over two decades ago she began
providing crucial support to
survivors of violence focusing
on women sex workers both cis
and transgender in the rural
areas of el salvador.
Her commitment to justice
and healing has been unwavering
ever since nicole's work with
the lgbtq plus community began
through art therapy
and research in el salvador
supporting survivors and anti
lgbtq I plus domestic
and sexual violence she
co-founded collective alejandro
sb, a groundbreaking
organization that collaborates
with ngos, activists
and government entities across
multiple countries to raise
awareness about the lived
realities of lgbtq plus
communities.
>> today nicole serves as the
executive director of air para
trans latinas, an organization
dedicated to empowering
and supporting trans latino
women with a trauma informed
approach.
She has strengthened ala's
programs, nurtured staff
development, fostered
partnerships and shared
sustained funding and served as
a powerful spokesperson for the
community.
Beyond her leadership, anna
nicole continues to be an
integral member of the
mesoamerican network of women's
human rights defenders.
She works tirelessly on a
global scale to advocate for
body autonomy for women,
intersex and trans people.
>> her work stands as a beacon
of unity, inclusion
and resilience demonstrating
what is possible when
compassion and determination
come together in the fight for
justice.
Nicole santa maria knows record
that la lucha board la justicia
e la inclusion natuna fronteras
suit rajo as soon testimonial
the bothered that I comunidad
isla this is estancia sigue I'm
also a templar icon throughout
the continuum was the fin the
los derechos that told us us
personas muchos gracias puerto
rico montana grasshopper to
sort our field there and which
has grasses at toll board of
supervisors thank you all for
this recognition my pronouns
are qiang we we because in my
indigenous tradition we are
recognizing that the I couldn't
exist without the we without
the community.
>> so receiving this
recognition for me it is their
recognition for our communities
for the entire communities of
the san francisco and beyond
because san francisco has been
the beacon of hope, the beacon
of faith especially for those
who have been marginalized for
their gender identities
and sexual orientations.
So here today I am happy to
receive this recognition but
in the personal level I am
really grateful because for an
indigenous woman as myself as
an intersex woman myself that
when I born I was told or
better said my parents were
told that I born with that
defect that is called
hermaphrodite tism so intersex
and being sent to the margins
and being kept quiet in a
country like south other
and being here in front of all
of you that means that all
women all women who have been
told in the past that they are
not worthy, that they cannot do
great things for their
communities.
This is a recognition for all
of them so humbly I accept this
in the name of all of our peers
but especially for those who
are in direct attacked in these
moments in our country that is
trans communities.
Our trans siblings are under
attack in this moment.
we have been under attack
several years ago but now more
than ever we need to stand
in solidarity, in allyship,
in bringing compassion humanity
to the front not a human being
is illegal.
No human being is not worthy.
So we are here to continue
building this society a better
society especially here in san
francisco there are no place
like home so let's make it
beautiful inclusive, thriving
together.
>> thank you.
District 11 supervisor chen
thank you, PRESIDENT
And colleagues today during
women's history month.
>> I'm so, so proud to honor
the wonderful and very
inspiring artists and activists
ealing willsboro when you come
off feeling yeah, give her a
big round of applause.
>> thank you ealing ealing was
born in the philippines
and migrated to the united
state in 1992.
>> for 15 years celia lived as
an undocumented immigrant.
And that experience shape who
who she is today her strength
in the face of hardship and her
steadfast commitment to helping
those around her and have
continue to influence her life
as an advocate.
Organizers, artists and a
mother yelling is the executive
director of the filipino
community center in district 11
serving no income families, low
wage workers and immigrants
filipinos makes up nearly 5% of
san francisco.
>> and yet the majority of the
immigrants san francisco
filipino community remains
underserved and underresourced
.
>> this evening's work as the
leader of the filipino
community center has been
crucial to helping the filipino
immigrant community overcome
barriers to economic stability
to gain access to essential
cultural and linguistic
resources.
>> for 20 years the fcc has
provided vital support services
and in doing so has gained the
trust and confidence of low
income immigrant filipino by
tirelessly advocating for her
community healing continues to
empower immigrants and working
and working class people in the
bay area and in philippines.
To this today the fcc continue
to bolster and uplift filipino
community and has expanded its
programs to include services
connection immigration
resources and referral
employment support for workers
advocacy, domestic violence
prevention, case management
and and award winning youth
development development program
and as and visual artists
taking after her father elaine
it's also inspired by the
people she encounters through
her work and creates drawings
paintings around the theme of
beauty hope with resistance
and community yelling as a wife
and a mother of two wonderful
boys learning the humble
responsibility of creating a
world that our children deserve
healing proves day after day
that is the strength of woman
in our immigrant communities
who so as the way forward
and I'm so proud to honor
eating today and please again
join me again to give her a big
round of us thank you any thank
you so much supervisor chen
thank you so much to the board
of supervisors.
>> you know I sometimes feel
awkward being recognized you
know being undocumented for 15
years.
The big thing that they teach
you when you're undocumented as
a child is you don't talk, you
don't make trouble.
You stay in the background
and you stay silent and you
make sure that you don't get
noticed at all.
>> and this is the complete
opposite of that I think
growing up as a undocumented
immigrant during the time where
there were no advocacy, there
were no words and there was no
big movement yet for immigrant
rights.
I had to grow up and realize
that my life experience was not
just my own that there are so
many like me.
>> there were so many like my
family and there are so many
more who are less fortunate
than what my family has gone
through.
And you know my work at the
filipino community center I
started there as a as a student
volunteer in the 2000s more
than 20 years ago.
And there I found a community a
place, a voice not only for
myself but for so many others
like me.
I realized that the more that I
spoke my my story spoke about
the injustices that my family
has gone through that I have
gone through and if I work
together with other immigrant
children, immigrant youth
and workers like me, like my
family that real power can
actually be created and given
to the communities that we that
we represent and what we
deserve.
>> 2030 years ago I would never
have thought that a person like
me could be recognized
in something like san francisco
city hall and even now you
know, working at the filipino
community center we represent
and work with filipino workers,
trafficked workers, caregivers,
youth who are underprivileged
or live in violence, women who
are struggling to survive here
economically while still
providing economic support for
their families back home in the
philippines.
>> you know, for those of us
who live in district 11, those
of us who work and live our
realities there, it is often
that we feel like we are
overshadowed by city hall.
>> we are so far away most
people think we are daly city
and maybe they're not that
wrong but you know your
recognition today, your
recognition of of our work, our
existence and the 11 and our
community's resilience to to be
firmly be a part of san
francisco to firmly fight for
our place here for our rights
and for a future that we all
deserve together show us that
you know, without the the the
ongoing work of people just
like myself when I was really
young and you know, even people
who are older than me, people
who have gone through so much
more challenging situations
that they're that progress, you
know, will not be made in san
francisco.
We are a part of that progress
and a recognition like this is
a recognition that low income
families, workers, undocumented
people, trafficked individuals
that economic justice is
women's women's advocacy, that
youth work is women's advocacy
that advocating for immigrants
and undocumented community is
advocating for women's rights.
And because we are all of those
and more you know, we
definitely see that the future
that we deserve is worth
fighting tooth and nail for.
And I'm I'm so proud
and honored to have been a part
of fcc to to have been a part
of this work, to have been a
part of the district
contributing to a better d11, a
better san francisco and the
filipino community center is
celebrating our 20th year
anniversary this year and you
know we wouldn't be here
without support from advocates
like you without the strength
of our the organizing of our
workers, our youth and our low
income families and we would
not be where we are as a whole
filipino community if it were
not for the sacrifices and the
advocacy and organizing of
hundreds and thousands of other
filipino low income and working
class people like those that
make up the filipino community
center.
Thank you so much for this
honor and we look forward to
continuing to work with you all
.
Do you think you thank you so
much.
>> next up district two
supervisor cheryl.
colleagues, today I am very
proud to recognize camryn
marlow for her incredible
leadership and service to the
people of san francisco.
Cameron is a sophomore at
liquid building high school of
our city tennis player a
special olympics swim coach
and district two is represented
on the san francisco youth
commission.
Accomplishing all this at only
16.
>> cameron was born and raised
in san francisco and her story
is a reminder that women's
history is being written right
now.
Her work shows us that the
future of this city is bright
and it is in good hands.
Cameron began serving her
community when she was just
nine years old volunteering at
a soup kitchen during the
height of the pandemic when our
elder community couldn't safely
leave their homes.
>> she cooked and delivered
meals to isolated seniors
through stepping stones.
But her passion for service has
only grown since.
Cameron has organized and led
donation drives for afghan
refugee children resettling
in northern california
partnering with five pillars to
provide backpacks and school
supplies.
>> she's worked with project
open hand to provide essential
items for unhoused san
franciscans.
She led an equipment drive for
youth tennis advantage
and expanding access to sports
for underserved youth.
And she's done it all while
being a full time student as a
youth commissioner for the city
and county of san francisco.
Cameron is a leading advocate
on issues that matter deeply to
our young people.
She's focused on improving
young youth mental health
especially when it comes to
social isolation.
She's also leading the charge
to make schools safer by
advocating for real solutions
to sexual violence in S.F..
Usd cameron is calling on S.F.
Usg to evaluate its background
check system so that no
offender can move from school
to school.
She is pushing for standardized
training and curriculum on
sexual harassment and assault
for both teachers and students.
She's also working to
strengthen the title nine
student advisory group to
ensure young people are always
present in the rooms where
decisions are made.
And as chair of the civic
engagement and education
committee on the youth
commission, cameron has written
policy and advocated directly
to district officials
stakeholders and even state
leaders.
And again she's accomplishing
all this while being a student.
Her work is serious.
Her commitment is real and her
leadership is already shaping
the future of our city.
>> cameron is an important
reminder to celebrate
and uplift the innumerable
inspiring young women
surrounding us all every day
right here in this building.
There are dozens of young women
just like her leading
departments shaping policy
literally keeping the city
running.
History isn't only something we
look back on.
It is something being made
every day by people like you,
cameron.
So on behalf of the board of
supervisors and with gratitude
from all of district two thank
you for your compassion and for
your courage and for your
incredible service to san
francisco.
Your legacy is already growing
and we can't wait to see what
you do next.
>> high board of supervisors
and MADAM Clerk thank you so
much.
Supervisor cheryl for honoring
me for women's history month.
Truly it's truly been an honor
to serve as the district
commissioner.
I initially joined the youth
commission because of my
interest in government
and public policy.
I never truly imagined the
impact that I could make among
the youth that I represent.
I hope to continue my journey
in public service and continue
to use my voice to address
topics I'm passionate about
such as addressing sexual
assault amongst youth
in schools, supporting youth
mental health initiatives,
especially addressing social
isolation and getting more
youth involved in public
service.
Growing up in san francisco has
shown me public service
and advocacy is a gateway to
making positive change in your
community.
Being a catalyst of improving
the lives of young of youth has
been a rewarding experience.
Again, thank you so much for
the recognition supervisor
cheryl and to the district
youth team for your support.
It really means a lot to me
.
>> district six supervisor
dorsey thank you PRESIDENT
Mandell man.
>> I'd like to ask sue betts to
approach the lectern and while
she does that I want to offer a
little background on the honor
I'm presenting today.
Not long after I was elected to
this board in NOVEMBER of 2022
when I finally knew for certain
that I would be around for four
years I had a conversation with
then PRESIDENT Aaron peskin
about the possibility of san
francisco city hall hosting a
regular weekly meeting for a
recovery community mutual help
group.
This wasn't simply about
finding space for a meeting
in any city owned building.
It was about the important
symbolism of uplifting our
city's vibrant and burgeoning
recovery community and sending
a message to anyone seeking
long term recovery from
addiction or alcoholism in this
town that here in san francisco
we are honored to host the
recovery community in nothing
less than the seat of
government itself.
>> as an out and proud fellow
brother in recovery himself,
aaron peskin readily agreed
and as one of our recovery
community's strongest allies,
PRESIDENT Rafael mandolin has
continued this tradition and we
are grateful for it.
But making space available for
just one hour a week was the
easy part.
The much harder part was to
find the leader from the
recovery community who would
not only agree to convene such
a meeting but hopefully create
a welcoming and supporting home
supportive home group that
would endure and thrive.
And there was one other wrinkle
because so many recovery
traditions are rooted
in spiritual and sometimes even
religious dimensions.
We also agreed that it might be
best to find a secular recovery
tradition given possible civil
liberties concerns of a
government building.
And it so happens there is such
a recovery tradition born right
here in the bay area 26 years
ago in MAY called life brings
secular recovery.
>> now again identifying the
right tradition was relatively
easy the hard part.
The secret sauce.
The factor that would determine
success or failure really
depended on the person who
stepped up to lead it.
And as we conclude women's
history month, it is my
privilege to honor an
extraordinary recovery
community leader in a field
where women are far too often
underrepresented.
Sue betz, CHAIRWOMAN Of the
board of life, rings secular
recovery.
Now sue sue was also the
inaugural convener of that
first ever alcohol
and addiction recovery meeting
here in city hall held every
friday at 12 noon and room 278.
The board conference room whose
growing attendance just
celebrated two years of active
participation last month in a
city that faces major
challenges related to substance
use and alcoholism, sue has
been a beacon of hope
and resilience creating
pathways to sobriety that are
inclusive, empowering and life
changing.
Sue joined life ring in 2019
and was encouraged shortly
thereafter to convene one of
life ring's original online
meetings.
The saturday morning chat sue
also created the liver spot
in 2020 and when she began
volunteering on life ring
committees in 2020 helped
establish the fundraising
marketing communications
committee affectionately known
as fund markham and she now
coordinates those efforts.
She also chairs the meetings
and convener collaboration team
and team outreach.
And not long after being
invited to join the life ring
board of directors, she went on
to serve as its chair.
Through her leadership with
life rings who has fostered a
welcoming and non-judgmental
space for individuals seeking
recovery on their own terms.
Her efforts in establishing
and sustaining both online
and in-person meetings have
been instrumental in helping
many find strength, solidarity
and self-empowerment in their
recovery journeys including I
don't mind sharing my own
recovery journey.
for her leadership to provide a
welcoming and essential
resource for city employees
and residents alike reinforcing
the importance of community
driven recovery efforts.
Sue betts continues to have a
profound impact not just in san
francisco but as part of a
broader movement for those
interested in secular
self-directed recovery.
Sue your tireless advocacy for
positive recovery choices has
changed lives.
On behalf of the city
and county of san francisco, we
offer this certificate as an
expression of our deepest
gratitude for your work, your
humor, your leadership.
Thank you for making our city a
better place for all san
franciscans especially those of
us in recovery.
>> congratulations sue batts
for us.
Well thank you supervisor
dorsey and I'm sorry little
choked up there.
Board of supervisors users
and happy women's history month
.
>> thank you for having me.
This woman's history isn't
exactly what you would call
textbook.
I certainly wouldn't want to
read about it.
But you know what?
Here's a brief synopsis
nonetheless the universe has a
dark sense of humor.
>> on APRIL fool's day 2019 I
blew up like violet beauregard
and wonka's chocolate factory
except I wasn't blue.
I was in an alarming shade of
yellow courtesy of stage four
alcoholic cirrhosis.
s.F. General hospital gave me a
stark choice quit drinking or
die.
>> it's really not much of a
choice but in the beginning it
was the beginning of a new
chapter.
>> written in bold print make
sobriety your top priority.
And I have and I try to help
support everyone I can because
this isn't just my story.
This it's the story of every
person who chooses recovery day
after day and those days add
up.
>> six years later I'm still
here.
I still have my original liver
and I'm still sober.
>> they say the best program is
the one that works for you.
>> and san francisco is rich
with resources.
Free residential treatment,
affordable sober living and a
wealth of peer led program
including of course my favorite
library secular recovery.
>> I was thrilled thrilled to
find the life ring meeting here
in keizer and us on fillmore.
And now it is my honor to
convene a library meeting here
in city hall.
>> we must keep the doors open
and keep the pathways clear to
ensure that everyone can find
recovery resources that
resonate with them and find the
connection within them.
>> let's honor compassion,
extend a hand to those
struggling and empower every
individual fighting for
sobriety.
Let's recognize that this work
provides vital resources that
allow people to reclaim agency
,rediscover purpose and find
their way back to themselves.
>> thank you, matt.
Oops sorry reviser darcy
and PRESIDENT Mendelsohn for
allowing us the space to
continue and to grow as people
in recovery.
>> and also to all the board of
supervisors for valuing the
power of choice and recovery.
>> stay strong.
Make good choices.
>> and make your history be
filled with stories worth
sharing.
>> thank you so much.
>> district four supervisor
and guardian.
Thank you.
Or I'd like to ask margaret
graff to come up to the podium
.
>> so this this women's history
month it is my honor to
recognize sunset resident
margaret graf.
We're celebrating margaret's
leadership in all four of her
careers.
Yes, for nurse, mother, lawyer
and community advocate.
She gave medical attention to
future PRESIDENT John f kennedy
.
She raised three kids.
She was a lawyer when few women
were in the courtroom.
And she advocates for senior
power today.
>> margaret is a woman that's
made lots of history at age 86
and we look forward to her
making more history.
In 1960 a young politician
entered her hospital clinic
in wisconsin asking for an
antibiotic shot for a nasty
cold he had.
Margaret administered the shot
to his backside and then she
talked to john f kennedy for
about 20 minutes and ended up
campaigning for him.
Later in the 1960s, margaret
left her career as a nurse
and moved to san francisco with
her husband paul.
>> they bought a house across
from the great highway where
margaret still lives today.
They raised three children
there.
Margaret always dreamed of
being a lawyer and attended law
school in the evenings.
Margaret became a defense
litigation attorney in her 40s.
She represented medical clients
when there were few women
in her specialty at the time.
Sometimes she was the only
woman in the courtroom.
After 20 years of law practice
,she retired in 2005.
Then she traveled the world
with her husband.
Sadly, tragedy struck when
their eldest daughter was
diagnosed with cancer.
Margaret cared for her until
she passed away.
And soon after her husband
developed alzheimer's disease
utilizing the skills from her
first career as a nurse.
>> margaret cared for paul for
six difficult years describing
it as the hardest job of her
life.
She looked everywhere for help
but information was not
centralized.
It was not until the city's
department of disability
and aging services invited her
and other caregivers to a study
group that she found community
and others facing the same
challenges.
This experience brought
margaret to her fourth career.
In 2018, margaret founded
senior power, a nonprofit
dedicated to empowering seniors
to care for their mental,
physical and emotional health.
>> and advocate for themselves
locally.
>> senior power evolved out of
necessity and blossomed into a
beautiful community resource.
When the pandemic closed a
terrible police station for
public meetings.
Margaret transitioned their
monthly meetings to a
newsletter to keep seniors
connected.
Senior power extended its reach
by starting a virtual zoom
program known as senior
connections where speakers from
ucsf school of medicine
and U.S. School of law discuss
general medical and legal
topics while creating a
community for sunset seniors.
Margaret met dorothy lathan who
I honored back in FEBRUARY for
black history month and dorothy
is here today again.
The women have lived two blocks
away from each other on the
great highway for over 60
years.
>> now I mentioned margaret for
careers but I think there might
be a fifth author.
>> margaret wrote her first
book in 2023 a children's book
about climate change.
And her second book is coming
in MAY.
Senior sharp essays and art on
aging.
Thank you, margaret, for being
a trailblazer trailblazer
and an advocate in san
francisco.
Thank you supervisor and guide
you.
>> at 86 I'm here for the
historic perspective on women a
very long time ago when I was
just a small child there were
few women heroes that could be
served as models in when I was
approximately six years old.
>> I started settling.
>> my women heroes.
I chose florence nightingale
because she went out into the
battlefield to care for the
sick and the wounded.
>> I chose annie oakley because
she was a really good horse
rider and she won all of her
shooting contests against men.
>> I chose eleanor roosevelt
because she was known for her
good works.
>> and though I was a little
fuzzy on what good works were,
I thought that was something
good to be in my own family.
>> there have been women heroes
much lesser accomplishment than
those I've named yet still
remarkable for their time.
>> my great great grandmother
fleeing a famine and a
turbulent political society
left europe to cross the ocean
and come to new york and then
from new york to go overland to
the midwest to marry a widower
twice her age.
>> she was a mail order bride.
I am the proud, great great
granddaughter of immigrants
and I have never forgotten that
I have an aunt, a great aunt
who walked the streets to help
women to have the right to vote
.
>> I have a grandmother who was
the first woman to own a car
in the county she lived in and
my own mother who had a tender
age of 13, was sent off to
boarding school so that she
could become the first in her
family to become a teacher.
>> women have come a long way
in seeking their heroes today.
>> the field is much broader
and the examples that we have
to look to are much more
diverse.
>> there are women astronauts,
software engineers, ceos of
companies.
>> we even came close to having
a woman PRESIDENT In my
lifetime.
>> please.
>> as I progressed through my
chosen careers I was almost
warned about a glass ceiling.
This was a term coined in 1978
and it came to mean
in referring to a supposed
limitation on professional
advancement.
>> yes, there have been clear
instances in my career when
I've been the only woman
present in a group of males
when I've been the only woman
who stood up and spoke.
>> but those days are gone.
They're retreating.
Even the glass ceiling is I
pushed upward.
It got thinner and finally I
discovered that all that was
holding me back was some thin
air.
>> so we've come a long way.
We've got a way to go.
>> to all of you young women
who are sitting here today come
stand on my shoulders.
Just as I stood on the
shoulders of everyone who came
before me just know I will
support.
>> I will push.
>> I will help.
Just know you are not alone
and a new generation will come
right behind you and I expect
you to do the same for them.
>> and for all the women whose
careers are behind them for
whom the upward challenge has
been reached.
>> come follow me.
Bring your intelligence, your
talents and your empathy.
Volunteer.
Your neighbors.
Your community.
Your city need you.
There is still history to be
made and we are not done yet.
>> thank you very much for this
honor.
>> it truly means a lot to me.
So for my part, conspiracies
out there right?
>> district five supervisor
mahmood can we have radwan
hussein and all her family
and friends come out all of you
come up come up.
Today in observance of women's
history month, it is an
absolute honor to recognize
someone who truly is the
embodiment of making it work
and honor and celebrate radwan
hussein a pillar in the
tenderloin community.
>> she's a remarkable community
leader who has dedicated her
time and energy to enriching
san francisco's diverse
communities.
She actually has a background
in veterinary medicine bringing
a deep sense of care
and compassion for all living
beings which eventually led her
to work at the tenderloin
community school and heavily
and heavy involvement in our
community.
>> she's the founder of early
learning arabic story hour at
the san francisco public
library helping children
connect with language
and culture and the joy of
reading.
Rodway also played a pivotal
role in organizing the first
ever eid celebration years ago
in the tenderloin creating a
space for families to come
together, celebrate and share
in the rich traditions of the
holiday and continues to be
instrumental in planning the
expansion of the event.
Stepping in where needed
organizing residents
and ensuring the community is
always centered in all
decisions.
>> I first met rothwell last
year during a read aloud at
tenderloin community school
which she helped organize an
event in which the majority of
students were first generation
children of color.
Her attention to ensuring
students have role models where
mirrors is part of the quiet
work she weaves into community
service at all times but
immediately struck me upon
meeting her was her warmth, her
kindness and almost stoic
calmness in an environment
where you have little ones
bouncing off the walls
and running around at 8 A.M. On
their way to the classrooms.
>> it was clear that she had
the temperament that only a
mother, a healer and a true
leader could have.
>> whether she's leading
community events uplifting
immigrant families or making
sure our youngest residents
have access to literacy
and cultural education,
rothwell is an inspiring force
for good.
>> and if you've ever had the
privilege of tasting her
cooking, you know she puts as
much heart into her food as she
doesn't her community.
>> I have not have that
privilege so I'm looking
forward to that with this
endless well of heart
and compassion is reflected
in conversations with her
colleagues at tcs who have
highlighted to us her
dedication, love for the
community and tireless efforts
to serve her community with
kindness, warmth and patience.
>> she's a vital part of the
heart of texas.
She leads and moves to this
work with her heart forward
consistently caring for others
in ways that are deeply
impactful and wildly
appreciated.
>> her calm and grounded
presence is his true strength
especially in the neighborhood
that she represents.
>> she is a careful observer, a
collector of human stories
and data that helps care for
students and families more
thoughtfully and intentionally
.
>> broadway has been crucial
in making connections with
community leaders
and organizations in her
capacity at tcs.
She has helped work towards
food security for families
in the neighborhood by securing
food boxes, donations from
multiple businesses and gift
cards from local grocery stores
like trader joe's, costco
and safeway.
>> she's gone further by
securing toy donations for
families both in the winter
and just this week.
Radway is also essential for
contacting our arabic speaking
families with school updates,
advertising community events,
encouraging family
participation and providing
behavior and discipline
information with families
in the tenderloin.
Her colleagues were thrilled to
report that tcs has seen
greater family involvement
since she began their.
>> when we spoke with them.
They couldn't agree more
and her deserved recognition
for this incredible work
and her impact in the
community.
>> so above all rawa is a
devoted mother, a leader
and someone who makes san
francisco a better place every
day.
We are lucky to have her in our
city, in our neighborhood
and in district five
and celebrate all her
contributions.
Thank you brother sal.
>> alaikum, everyone.
Peace be upon you all.
I want to start by thanking you
all for being here today.
I am filled with joy
and gratitude to being on earth
today.
As a mother, a working woman,
an arab and muslim I want to
give a special thanks to my
husband ahmed and my wonderful
children yaseen and zain who
despite being a little bit
upset for me for picking them
up early from school.
>> but they are here by my
side.
>> your love and support means
the world to me and keep me
going.
>> I am also deeply grateful to
my entire tender loving
community especially might
interline community school
coworkers who are here today
and those who couldn't make it
but have been showering me with
love all day.
>> like a real family.
Your love, your hugs, your
kindness, your kindness
and encouragement remind me why
I do what I do.
>> a heartfelt thank you to
supervisor bilal mahmood for
this incredible honor your
support and believe in us.
Make a real difference in the
face of the challenges that
immigrant communities are
facing right now and the
current struggle in the middle
east.
>> weighing weighing heavy on
our hearts very heavy.
This recognition is a ray of
hope, a reminder that our
efforts are seen and valued.
It encouraged us to keep
striving, contributing
and making a difference.
Thank you again for this
meaningful honor.
>> assalamu alaikum, ma'am.
I hope I get them.
Thank you.
>>
and now if trend saying could
come on up.
>> this commendation is
bittersweet for me but it is my
honor on this final tuesday of
women's history month to
present a special commendation
to trenton who is going to be
stepping down from her role as
chief executive officer at prc
at the end of next month.
>> and that's the better part.
>> many of you are familiar
with prc and the important work
they do in san francisco.
For those who are not prc
formally positive resource
center provides legal, medical
and housing assistance to
people struggling with
addiction hiv aids mental
health challenges under un or
underemployment
and homelessness.
>> when tran took over as ceo
of prc and some of the folks
in this chamber will remember
the organization was struggling
financially and had had to come
before this board seeking
emergency assistance to keep
its doors open.
>> tran and her team turned it
around.
They designed and implemented
prc's financial stabilization
strategy restructuring programs
to renegotiating contracts
and strengthening financial
oversight.
Within just a year hurley her
leadership brought prc back to
financial stability achieving
net positive revenues
and lifting the organization
off the comptroller officer's
watch list.
Today under her direction prc
remains one of the city's
preeminent wraparound service
providers delivering support to
more than 5000 san franciscans
annually and doing so in a way
that is sustainable for the
organization.
Tran began her work with
positive resource center as a
staff attorney at a recent law
school graduate back in 2009
representing low income clients
through the disability claims
process.
>> she was a founding member of
a set of S.F. Hiv fog that's
frontline organizing group a
program that now operates under
prc's umbrella of services
in its early days.
S.F. Hiv fogg was an entirely
volunteer driven effort a small
group of community providers
who saw a need to support hiv
frontline workers and took
action without city funding.
They organized trainings based
on topics frontline workers
requested relying solely on
their own volunteer time.
Seeing the programs value the
department of public health
eventually funded it.
What began as a grassroots
grassroots effort with no
listserve mentor program
educational campaigns or paid
positions has since evolved
into a comprehensive city
backed initiative serving san
francisco's hiv service
providers.
>> in 2013 tran took a position
with the national league of
cities in washington, D.C.
Helping to connect american
families with critical health
care programs like medicaid
and the children's health
insurance program.
After the affordable care act
passed, tran returned to san
francisco to head up the new
equal access to health program
at prc.
>> that program came out of a
city taskforce that was looking
into how passage of the aca
might affect san francisco
residents living with hiv.
>> at the time there was nobody
in the city working on health
care law specifically for hiv
positive folks.
Tren provided consultations for
community partner providers
assessing available health care
options, navigating
interactions between different
programs and offering brief
consults or representation as
needed.
She worked closely with case
managers at clinics
and agencies that provide case
management services for people
living with hiv aids.
>> prior to the affordable care
act, just 25% of prc clients
had health care access thanks
to the aca and trends work
in connecting clients to care.
>> 71% of prc clients obtained
health care coverage coverage.
>> in all her roles as prc
staff attorney supervising
attorney, managing legal
director, chief of programs,
chief of client services
and talent and for the last two
and a half years ceo tran has
combined her remarkable hard
and soft skills with an
extraordinary heart for
service.
Whether she was conducting
legal consultations, launching
innovative programs, connecting
people to health care or saving
one of san francisco's most
essential hiv and behavioral
health service providers, her
focus has always been on
lifting up the most vulnerable
members of our community.
Thank you trend for your steady
leadership your commitment to
serving the most vulnerable
and your heart.
We're deeply grateful for your
service and wish you the very
best in your future endeavors.
And now the floor is yours.
>> gosh, thank.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT
Randleman for your recognition
and your honor and thank you to
the entire board of supervisors
.
>> this is an incredibly
incredible privilege for me to
be amongst inspiring women
throughout our community.
I want to recognize that while
I'm being named on the pamphlet
and celebrated today, this is a
recognition of our clients our
clients with hiv, our clients
with mental health disabilities
and people living with
substance use disorders.
>> I want to recognize our
staff who's here behind me the
wonderful team of senior
leaders and direct services
providers that this is a
recognition of.
I want to recognize our board
to darren smith who's our
representative here today and I
want to recognize my family, my
son, my husband and my parents
,my mom who is is the example
of women leadership.
>> thank you.
I am emotional because looking
back at 14 years at prc
and serving this city, you put
your there you put your heart
and soul into it.
>> yes.
And I'm glad that we were able
to see prc with your
partnership to do right by our
city.
>> and I'll just say as I was
listening to the remarks from
margaret, you know, it might
feel like it's thin air that's
holding us back but for me it
was more a reckoning that it
was myself stepping into
leadership was about me holding
myself back.
And for any women leaders who
are exploring leadership, I
would say lean into yourself
your own confidence, what you
can bring your skill set
and your talent and believe
that you can deliver.
And I think delivery is
critical but it's the manner
in which you deliver which is
even more important.
So thank you to the board.
Thank you to our PRESIDENT.
I really appreciate your honor
thank you to the city.
>> thank you.
Tran and thanks to your mom.
>> yeah.
Thank you.
Years yeah.
Yeah yeah, yeah.
Okay.
And everybody now ap women's
history month everybody thank
you supervisor melgar to you
and your staff for getting us
organized and I think that
takes us back to roll call.
>> MADAM Clerk 3 P.M. Special
order MS. Oh, you are correct.
It takes us to our 3 P.M.
Special order.
>> could you call our 3 P.M.
Special order?
Yes.
Items 22 through 25 comprise
the special order at 3 P.M..
This is a public hearing of
persons interested in the
approval of a conditional use
authorization for a proposed
project at 4100 third street to
establish for use greater than
6000ft2 in size and to convert
an existing two story over a
basement mixed use building
with eight group housing units
at the second floor into an
approximately 6123 square foot
social service facility for use
within the nct the moderate
scale neighborhood commercial
transit district zoning
district third street alcohol
special use district and 60 5-j
height and bulk district items
2324 and 25 are the motions
associate did with this appeal.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk
supervise the dorsey thank you
PRESIDENT Mandolin
in accordance with the agenda
and at the request of
supervisor walton and whose
district this is I would like
to make a motion today to
continue these items to the
APRIL 8th meeting.
All right.
Thank you.
There's a motion to continue
till the eighth.
It's been seconded motion by
supervisor dorsey seconded by
supervisor chen and MADAM Clerk
.
>> can you call the roll on
that motion or do we need to
take up but we need to call
public comment on the
continuance?
>> yes.
Is there anyone here in the
chamber who would like to make
public comment on the
continuance for items 22
through 25?
>> all right, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right.
Public comment on the
continuance is close.
All right.
We have a motion to continue
this hearing to APRIL eighth
and I guess can we take that?
>> will I have lost track?
>> let's call the roll on the
motion to continue items 22
through 25 to APRIL 8th.
>> supervisor cheryl cheryl
eyes supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and engardio
and engardio eyes supervisor
field her field her eyes
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor randleman I mandal
man I and supervisor melgar
melgar I there are nine eyes
all right without objection
this appeal hearing and motions
are continued to APRIL 8th 2020
five and then we can go back to
roll call roll call for
introduction introductions.
Next up to introduce new
business supervisor chan thank
you.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk
colleagues today I'm
introducing a resolution to
declare that the city
and county of san francisco is
a sanctuary for women seeking
housing.
According to our community
partner community for in san
francisco every night there are
an estimated 3200 women
experiencing homelessness.
Of these of those women over
90% have or will experience
some form of violence in their
lives.
>> additionally, survivors of
domestic violence are at
greater risk of homelessness
and that nearly 1 in 5
cisgender homeless woman
endured physical violence or
abuse from their partner in a
six months prior to losing
their housing even while
knowing these staggering
statistics federal funding for
crime victim support has
dropped by 37% from 2023 to
2024 and the state has
allocated a one time emergency
funding to close this gap
in san francisco we must do
more.
Studies have shown that stable
safe housing is key to prevents
the revictimization of
survivors and their children.
The resolution I bring to you
today calls upon our city
agencies to work together to
create a collaborative,
sustained effort to ensure
women particularly survivors of
gender based violence have
access to safe, affordable
housing and essential services
.
>> and colleagues, I also want
to remind you that this is not
only from this based on this
resolution and our community
advocates but also really san
francisco voters san francisco
voters in 2024 last year
actually also voted for a
affordable housing bond that's
including woman shelter today
in 2025 in MARCH a year later
we have yet to see that funding
allocated and that woman
shelter is waiting for us to
push this forward and I really
urge our city agency to work
hard, harder and to make this a
reality.
Many women's as indicated
in this resolution are waiting
for this so thank you to
supervisors mal ga chen
and felder for your early co
sponsor schip and the rest I
submit.
>> thank you.
Thank you supervisor chan.
>> supervisor chen so submit
thank you.
>> supervisor dorsey thank you
MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, I offer an
in memoriam today to therese
lee coates the second T.S. To
those who know him and ask that
we adjourn today's board of
supervisors meeting
in remembrance of him as the
beloved son, father, friend,
artist and member of the san
francisco community.
He was there as was deeply
loved by his family and friends
and despite struggles he faced
over many years with addiction,
mental illness and a life lived
on and off the streets, he was
never alone in his fight.
Many san franciscans learned of
their offices passing in news
reports published over the
weekend in two stories about a
life's journey that included
hope and heartbreak in the san
francisco chronicle and in
mission local we learned that
tse had a place waiting for him
in a drug program this week to
which he would never make it.
He passed away last thursday
in county jail and as always
in the case of in-custody
fatalities his death will be
investigated by the medical
examiner's office, department
of police accountability
and criminal investigations
unit of the sheriff's office.
Like his father, therese coates
senior.
Those who knew and loved T.C.
Remember him as a generous
friend and family member a
person of devout faith.
Baptized into jesus christ at
the age of 12.
A student who earned a
scholarship to college in texas
and a talented musician
and gospel rapper who left
behind an impressive collection
of music.
>> he was also a father
himself.
And while he is troubled, life
was cut short at just 33 years
of age, his enduring love for
his daughter and his wider,
wider family was undeniable.
It was two his inestimable
progress that led promise that
led so many to fight so
relentlessly to help him.
There are senior did everything
in his power to get his son the
care and support he needed
in so many ways as dedicated
and loving a parent as one
could want.
There are seniors stood by T.C.
Through his darkest hours
advocating for him searching
for resources and enlisting the
help of a member of the board
of supervisors.
Never giving up hope for
recovery.
When I spoke to htc's dad to
express my condolences a few
days ago he let me know that
T.C. Was working on a cd that
he had nearly finished under
his artist name trilogy the
minister.
It will be farriss seniors
mission to release that cd
sometime later this year.
Htc's mother andrea coates too
fought tirelessly to get to see
the help he needed highlighting
the urgent need for stronger
interventions and resources for
those battling addiction
and severe mental health crises
on our streets.
The unwavering commitment of
tc's family to hope for his
recovery is a testament to the
strength of one family's love
and unshakable faith a love
and faith that despite many
systemic barriers never wavered
as we remember there is coates
today we are reminded that few
issues confronting major cities
are as challenging or
heartbreaking as addiction
driven and mental health
related unsheltered
homelessness.
And that the work we do to
strengthen our mental health
and addiction services has
never been more important to
our city and to countless
loving families like tess's.
Tc is uncle richard beale is
the director of recovery
services at the tenderloin
housing clinic.
He happens also to be someone I
consider a friend and among the
wisest, most inspiring members
of the recovery community I
know.
When I called richard to
express my condolences
personally for the loss of his
nephew, he shared with me that
he sees life and loss as even
now serving as an inspiration
for the creation of a new
organization called brothers
against drug deaths an advocacy
and support organization for
black men in the recovery
community.
For all of us who work to get
therapies coates the support he
needed.
I think there is comfort
and hope in knowing that even
in its loss his life is
inspiring efforts to give back
to those who struggle with
substance use disorders and to
offer others a chance for
recovery.
It would sadly elude to himself
our condolences to all who
loved therapist lee tsai coates
the second especially his
parents therese and andrea
and his siblings terrell,
shania and celeste.
MAY he rest in peace at last
and MAY his memory be a
blessing.
>> and the rest I submit.
Thank you supervisor dorsey
supervisor and engardio.
Colleagues today I am
introducing a good governance
ordinance to remove barriers
and red tape for basic backyard
storage.
I know many west side
homeowners have backyard garden
and storage sheds and many of
these structures have existed
for decades without inspections
complaints or stamped permits.
But the moment a homeowner
decides to start on a basic
improvement project, they're
required to navigate our
complex building and planning
codes and this can be a
daunting experience.
And it shouldn't have to be
this way.
It shouldn't be required to
have a law degree to know what
can and cannot be done with
your backyard.
We need to make government less
confusing and more accessible
to regular residents.
A simple home improvement
project like a storage shed
should not require a public
hearing countless hours
navigating code with building
and planning staff or the
prospect of steep fines
and penalties.
This legislation intends to
clarify what people can do with
their backyards.
and thank you colleagues.
I hope to have your support on
this piece of common sense
legislation.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you supervisor
and engardio supervisor fielder
.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I am offering
an in memoriam in honor of
curtis kimble, a former long
time district nine resident
and a vibrant and beloved
community member who passed
away far too young on FEBRUARY
19th at the age of 46.
>> curtis called san francisco
home for 20 years and was known
to many san franciscans as the
creme brulee guy and later as
the pancake guy.
>> in 2009 curtis started his
creme brulee cart and his
mission garage and alongside
his brother bryan's magic curry
cart you would see the two
parked near the mission
playground park or dolores park
.
Both brothers wearing chef hats
and jackets serving up amazing
treats.
Later the creme brulee cart was
stationed in the castro serving
up all manner of unique
and classic flavors.
You didn't have to know curtis
that long to feel magic.
He would smile and engage with
everyone telling witty jokes
while torching the tops of his
creative creme brulee
concoctions.
Curtis was fueled by his deep
love and affinity for san
francisco and it brought him
great joy to add quirky and fun
experiences to the community
centered around his special
spins on classic foods.
During covid, curtis felt
and lamented the loss of
personal connections that so
many of us experienced during
those early days of the
pandemic.
In response he decided to serve
free pancakes outdoors for his
preceded park neighbors.
Curtis said it was because his
wife told him he was getting
weird and needed to make
friends.
Curtis hung fliers around the
neighborhood inviting all to
come together.
Over 75 people came to his
first party hundreds attended
the second.
What started as a lighthearted
way to make friends turned into
a movement that gained a lot of
attention.
He was featured in the new york
times, washington post
and media outlets nationally as
curtis once wrote quote I'm
making pancakes to make friends
and making pancakes to spread
love and making pancakes so
that you'll make pancakes
and you'll spread love because
though I MAY love making food,
it's the people that make it
magic.
At the end of the day or in the
beginning if it's breakfast
we're all hungry to connect.
>> but the accomplishment that
curtis was most proud of was
his family.
This includes marrying his wife
nicole, with whom he would love
to link build their sweet
family.
>> curtis was a caring father
to his daughters harper
and louise and his soon to be
son arriving this summer.
i want to offer my most deep my
deepest condolences to curtis
parents julie and william
campbell, his brother bryan
and especially his wife nicole
and his children harper eloise
and his son who is on the way.
Rest in peace and power.
Curtis kimball.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder supervisor
my would submit thank you.
>> supervisor randleman thank
you MADAM Clerk.
>> today I am introducing a
couple of resolutions to
initiate a historical landmark
district designation for two
small districts in the mission
dolores neighborhood the chula
alley chula abby and alert
alley early residential
historic districts.
This board has done significant
work and will continue to do
that work to increase
and expand development capacity
in the city.
We will be considering
significant up zoning later
this year and if all this works
the way it is supposed to,
we're going to see a lot of
housing development in san
francisco at some point when
the money turns back on
and that is generally to the
good and positive for our
economy and for our ability to
accommodate more folks.
>> I do want to make sure that
as we do that we are careful
and identify the actual
historic resources that we want
to see preserved and not lost
as development goes forward.
So that's what we're doing in a
pretty small way in the mission
dolores neighborhood.
we've worked with the mission
dolores neighborhood
association.
I particularly want to thank
peter lewis and erin phillips
over there.
They've been working on this
for many, many years.
I think the entirety of my time
on the board of supervisors
and before I want to thank p la
la valley and rich sue cray
from planning for their work.
I want to thank andrea russo
ski day and peter million each
from the city attorney's office
and I want to thank calvin
and my office and the rest I
submit.
>> thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar thank you
MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I am joined by
supervisors fielder walton chen
mahmood and cheryl
in introducing it hearing on
thursday APRIL 17th at 4 P.M.
To discuss the implementation
of the student success fund
and a corresponding motion to
convene a joint select city
and school district committee
to schedule that hearing.
As many of you know, this board
and the voters supported the
creation of the student success
fund which is source by access
education revenue augmentation
fund era dollars to invest
funding to our school district
.
This fund is meant to support
innovative solutions that focus
on student academic outcomes
and to support the social
emotional health of students
most impacted by the pandemic.
These dollars are administered
by the city through cyf we have
seen some incredible success of
of intervene funds are funded
by this student success fund
like for example the whole math
the whole school lesson study
math pilot program which has
produced in improvements of as
much as 20% for students
they're not only doing well but
finding joy in learning,
in learning math and we need to
do more of this.
>> however, there's been
growing confusion on how to
most efficiently gap the
student success fund grants out
to school sites and how to
address potential constraints
on hiring given the school
district's budget stabilization
process and the guidance from
california department of
education.
>> as such, we we feel it's
timely and necessary to bring
various stakeholders to a
public setting inclusive of dcf
,the school district and the
department of education
representatives to answer
questions and clarify next
steps so that we can ensure
that the student success fund
can meet our city, our voters
intent to invest in our
students during a really
challenging time.
We believe it would be best to
hold this hearing on the
student success fund by
convening a one time joint
select city and school district
committee which will be
comprised of three members of
the school board and three
members from our board of
supervisors which will be
supervisor field or supervisor
walton and myself.
We welcome all of you of course
and school board commissioners
to attend as well.
>> I look forward to this
hearing and your support for
this motion to convene the
special committee next I am
introducing a resolution
condemning the federal
administration's unlawful use
of the alien enemies act to
detain and deport venezuelan
immigrants without due process.
>> this action represents yet
another example of dangerous
overreach of executive power
and a direct attack on
constitutional protections.
>> the alien enemies act first
enacted in 1798, has been used
very sparingly in our nation's
history only during declared
wars such as world war two.
Yet today it is being misused
to justify mass deportations
under the false pretense that
the violent actions of a few
constitute constitute an
invasion by venezuela.
>> the misuse of this act has
alarmed many many communities
but particularly the japanese
american community who has
painful history with this war.
>> during world war two this
law was invoked to detain
japanese, german and italian
nationals leading to the
incarceration the incarceration
of over 120,000 people of
japanese ancestry.
Despite a ruling yesterday by
the U.S. District court
striking down the use of the
alien enemies act, the federal
administration has forcibly
deported over 200 venezuelan
immigrants to el salvador where
they face indefinite detention
and conditions condemned for
human rights abuses.
In 1942 it was japanese
nationals.
Today it is people from
venezuela.
We cannot go back to those days
.
>> the rule of law is the
defining american principle.
Our cities have long stood for
due process, civil liberties
and fundamental human rights.
Therefore I urge my colleagues
to support this resolution
in join me join me in calling
on the federal government to
seize this illegal enforcement
and reaffirm san francisco's
commitment to justice and the
rule of law.
>> lastly, I rise today to
mourn the loss of justice
timothy reardon, a man whose
life exemplified integrity
service and love for the city
and the family.
>> born and raised in san
francisco, justice reardon
carried forward a family legacy
of leadership and civic
dedication.
His decades of service as a
respected and fair minded
jurist left an indelible mark
on california's legal
community.
>> beyond the courtroom,
justice reardon was a man of
deep faith a devoted husband,
father, grandfather and a
mentor to many.
>> his legacy lives on through
his children his son tim junior
and daughters liz and carrie
who are dedicated catholic
school educators.
Tim at archbishop reardon high
school in carrie and liz at
saint cecilia.
>> his daughter sharon followed
in his footsteps to become a
san francisco superior court
judge.
On behalf of district seven
and the entire board of
supervisors, I extend my
heartfelt condolences.
Condolences to the reardon
family.
MAY his memory be a blessing
and MAY we continue to honor
his extraordinary life
and contributions to san
francisco.
>> thank you.
The rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor melgar.
And I believe that that
completes roll call.
So let's go to public comments.
>> at this time the board
welcomes general public
comment.
As you are lining up on your
right hand side of the chamber
along the curtains as MADAM
Clerk stated earlier, we will
first hear remote public
comment from the person
requesting an ada accommodation
.
But I have just received notice
they are not on the line so
we'll go ahead to our in-person
callers.
You MAY speak on the approval
of the minutes as presented
general matters that are not on
the agenda but must be within
the board subject matter
jurisdiction.
>> all other agenda contact
will have been reported out to
the board by the appropriate
committee where the public
comment requirement occurred.
>> first speaker we will
provide two minutes of this.
>> I'm not can that be that it
should be my last meeting.
It's an order from this guy
you're going to leave not to
have to deal with unfortunately
your low level of intelligence
guys you know where it comes
from technology technology
lowers everyone's intelligence
especially now digital
technology.
>> that's the way it works for
everybody has become so dumb
it's unbelievable but true.
>> so I'm going to be leaving
you.
That's fine.
You won't see me my last
meeting will be tomorrow
actually with the fire because
we are under odds.
>> I just you know, I told you
you are in danger.
Okay?
Air means absolute incompetence
.
>> define us.
The inability to even
understand out to justify one's
reasons for being which is to
be happy focusing on the
eternal emotional aspiration to
world beauty as the rules of
existence explain so where do
you think it ends?
>> you are killing your soul.
>> you are very shots you won't
be much let me remind you
something if you kill someone
with that self defense directly
or indirectly your soul is
done.
You will never be back.
This is the end of your
existence.
>> your shield went before you.
So imagine now you are taking
orders basically from whoever
this old intelligence that
wants to control the world when
it done which is already dead.
>> so you are taking orders
stupidly enough from the dead
the and you expect the future.
>> I think you do stupidly
enough.
>> like I said, your own
intelligence zero underground
or the good diner.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
Good afternoon board of
supervisors.
For the record my name is chris
ward klein.
Before I start I wanted to do a
point of information that there
was information that was
referenced to a former
supervisor and that is outside
the acceptable guidelines.
I want to talk about systemic
racism which that kind of leads
to and basically what happened
in the 70s is happening again
in san francisco.
I submitted an fbi report
that's not the work of just me.
It's one hundreds of
investigators.
Please read it.
What happened in the 70s san
francisco allowed a foreign
country and the caribbean to
use their military systems to
illegally influence san
francisco and other cities
and counties.
It led to the invasion of
grenada.
If you are not aware there are
troops going to the border
and there are military ships
going down there right now
because it's going to happen
again if they don't turn the
systems off.
This report identifies your
city attorney and your former
city attorney as culpable.
Very culpable.
They are under investigation.
To make matters worse, the cdc
health and human services just
said that they are pulling back
$11 billion of funding to san
francisco.
That's over 1 billion for
california, about 300 million
for san francisco.
Good luck.
In addition to that.
The stanford coach was fired.
Sec I still can't get you said
stanford being in the sec
and just read the report.
And then the last week I've
been spending a lot of time
reaching out to the baptist
church, the glide church,
jonathan butler, the ncaa
and the acp and multiple news
people.
Wall street journal, new york
times, L.A. Times.
San francisco chronicle.
They have a copy of this
and they are investigating it
as well.
You need to use your pressure
to have the city attorney
and dennis hopper resign
effectively immediately.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hello supervisors
supervisors.
Happy women's history month.
My name is eve langston bartow
and the chief policy officer
for sam's club safe house
and the co-chair for the
women's housing coalition.
I'm here today on behalf of the
women's housing coalition to
thank supervisor chang for
introducing the resolution for
better protections for unhoused
and low income women of san
francisco, the department of
homelessness and supportive
housing.
This latest point in time count
estimated that there 3176 women
are sleeping on the streets
today and we know that that
number is low.
>> over 40% of the women
and gender non-conforming
peoples make up the homeless
population yet 95% of our
housing are occupied by men.
>> today providers all over the
state of california are calling
for the governor to ensure that
victims of crime act funding be
preserved because for many
women and women services
providers this is their only
sole lifeline.
>> we continue attacks
nationally now more than ever
as san francisco needs to take
a lead and do what it must to
provide safety, security
and housing specifically for
women.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker, I.
My name is annapurna.
I'm a district three resident
and a voter.
I took off many hours today to
come and speak with you all.
I spent an hour on the bus.
I spent the entirety of the
meeting here and I'll be
attending another hour on the
bus to go back to get back this
past this past wednesday the 19
bus was over fall.
I watched many people be unable
to get onto the bus the next
day on thursday the 49 was over
fall and I watched people
including those with
wheelchairs unable to get onto
the bus.
I take the bus four times a
week at minimum for over an
hour.
So I come and speak not just
for myself and not just
in solidarity with those that
were had a rally recently
and not just but I come
and speak for every single
person that uses the bus.
>> I come and speak for every
single san francisco and when I
say that we cannot allow
service to be cut, we cannot
allow for us to only have a
mirage of service.
And I urge the board of
supervisors to authorize a
general transfer from the
general fund to the two to help
save muni effectively.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hi all I'm lisa
platt from d2.
>> everyone agrees that cutting
muni service is bad especially
the 250 people who took off
work to attend the rally last
week and the 64 who stayed
several hours to give public
comment.
And these proposed summer cuts
impact many districts cutting
riders to downtown in d three
and d six reducing service for
the students who ride the bus
home from school in d one and d
two and beating the out of
access for d five all as their
family needs is $7.2 million to
stop the summer cuts they found
the reston savings if you all
do a general fund transfer of
that small amount we can save
muni or even split the
difference with them and do
matching 3.6 million general
fund if they commit the 3.6
from their reserves but you
can't count on the state or
federal government to fix this
for us we need to figure out
how to help ourselves.
>> americans are desperate for
leaders who will stand up for
the people.
>> right now we're worn down by
the weak compromises
and excuses as san franciscans
are feeling this assault more
than others are immigrants.
>> our values and our parks are
all under siege this is when we
need you most.
We need your voice, your
strength and for you to
represent us in a way you know
is right.
>> you all are in a position to
positively impact our economic
recovery and the lives of
everyday san franciscans.
>> you have the opportunity
today to stand up for something
that is so crucial to the
fabric of the city.
Transit saving muni is the
small win we all desperately
need to keep us fighting
and not giving up.
>> it's inexpensive in relation
to the overall budget but rich
in rewards.
Please do a general fund
transfer to not be the
administration that lets muni
fail.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> hi my name is sonia herrera.
I'm a district three resident
and a volunteer with muni now
muni forever.
I am pleading with the board of
supervisors to transfer monies
from the general fund to the
mta.
This many money can help
prevent service cuts proposed
for this summer.
Today was a markedly warm day
at least for me.
i can't imagine how seniors
feel walking to their bus stops
waiting in the sun for their
bus to arrive.
>> if the mta cuts bus service
this summer such as in the
manner discussed here at city
hall last week, the city's most
elderly bus riders will be hit
the hardest.
The agency has proposed that a
number of bus routes stop
running at market street for
passengers riding these bus
lines they will have to exit
their bus walk to a transfer
point and then wait for another
bus.
>> hopefully the distance isn't
too far and the weather is not
too bad.
>> hopefully these seniors can
catch their next bus on time.
>> by making such cuts we make
life much harder for residents
who have already paid their
dues in this life.
Please do what you can to
prevent this cut in bus service
at least until we have a real
chance of getting more money
for muni.
>> thank you all for sponsoring
the resolution calling for the
governor and state legislature
to save public transit.
>> please continue this
movement by following the lead
of supervisors chen fielder,
mahmood and melgar and showing
your local support for muni
writers.
>> please approve a general
fund transfer to the mta.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
My name is bradley dunn and I'm
the manager of local government
and community relations for
bart.
I wanted to speak in support of
item number 31 urging the
governor and state legislature
of california provide
multi-year operations funding
and develop a long term funding
plan to support bay area
transit agencies.
Bart wants to thank the board
for this resolution and your
FEBRUARY vote in support of
secure ongoing funding not just
for muni but also for bart.
Bart is essential lifeline
and as you know carrying
thousands of bay area and san
francisco residents to school
family and their communities.
Bart is also critical for
downtown recovery and brings
workers, shoppers and patrons
of the arts downtown to to our
businesses and to support those
institutions.
About 115,000 bart trips start
or end in san francisco on an
average weekday and about
97,000 of those are to or from
downtown.
Bart needs additional funding
to continue to provide high
quality transit service.
Other regions recognize the
benefits of public transit
and how it protects the
environment, supports our
economy, enhances livability
and those communities choose to
tax themselves to pay about 67%
of their regional rail
transit's operating costs.
Unfortunately the bay area
in contrast only pays for about
41% of bart's operating costs
through taxes riders have to
pay for the rest being reliant
on fares to pay for operations
has left us with significant
deficits in the face of remote
work and office vacancies.
While we have recovered about
76% of our riders, those riders
are taking one less trip a week
and our revenue is about half
of what it was before the
pandemic.
We've been trying to run
efficiently and have closed our
$35 million fiscal year 26
budget through cost
efficiencies.
But that budget deficit reopens
again in fiscal year 27.
If stable funding is an
identified we might have to cut
service run once power stations
or and that's going to be
really hard to maintain the
ridership that brings people to
downtown san francisco to make
it a lively, vibrant place.
>> so we're very thankful for
your efforts in this matter.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
I appreciate supervisor fiedler
you mentioned about desert city
four weeks ago I lived
in zurich.
I left work in 1990 and moved
to san francisco.
San francisco above zurich.
There's no doubt zurich is
still beautiful.
I want to speak german
and italian because I learned
two languages over there.
>> suitcase wunderbar suitcase.
>> secret customs.
Zurich cyber security.
Zurich physician insurance work
is obvious why yorick left
in the zurich ish context
forgotten stick box reporter
mark newton gold in zurich.
Molto pierre tessuti go malta
police to sligo molto bella
bellissimo sligo.
You absolutely do any mg here.
Supervisor fiddler.
>> but back to laurel o'keeffe
.
>> two years ago new york city
taxi meter about $6 and sun
protecting me drivers 350 no
taxi meter drop in zurich city
is 12 swiss franc which is more
than $13.
>> son of a taxi meter drop is
$4.15 which is ridiculous
and uber is banned in zurich.
Zurich taxi drivers income
double after covid.
Sunflower taxi drivers income
dropped 95%.
Our demand is very reasonable.
We are not asking for any
donation.
We are asking for our money
back.
That money was earned with our
blood and sweat.
>> it is a massacre of poor
immigrant taxi drivers city
created this mess.
>> city has to clean up this
mess which has to do many times
lower the price on medallions
to 125.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
It's same same thing like about
the taxi issue but we feel like
we will get released sooner.
Something will happen.
And then something bad
happened.
Like I was at the airport
and two days ago they give me a
letter they say here you did
the violated the law.
>> you pick somebody from city
drop him in the airport and you
charge the 550 airport fees
which was false.
I didn't never do that.
>> and then next day they say
you will be for six months you
will be probated.
>> and then today they're
calling me.
They say I'm sorry there was
all error.
You're okay.
You're fine.
You have nothing to do.
So I don't know why they're
harassing us for what reason?
And then there's a ramp cab.
They pick up their one
passenger and then they reset
the meter three times with the
same one passenger.
So they collect $60 from the
city $20 each and then they
make that short and then they
go to the airport and we sit
there for hours and the rent
cab they're making like trips
they're making the money from
here from mta and then from the
passenger.
So this is not fair so please
pay attention to that and at
least as far as we don't have a
fix, the problem so we have the
extra extra problem.
We just want you to please let
them know don't don't hit us
just like that.
We're working people and we
already have so much trouble we
cannot pick anymore.
>> thank you so much.
Appreciate it.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker good afternoon
supervisors.
My name is robin krop and I'm
going to touch briefly on two
topics.
>> the first one is the 7.2
million dollar deficit that
muni has.
I am an idea we have a lot of
wealth in this city and I'm
wondering whether the city has
reached out to wealthy
individuals, organizations or
companies that might like to
help out with that deficit.
So that's just a question I
want to put to you.
>> now I'm here to talk about
my friend david hart.
So who passed this past
saturday and he lived in the
haight ashbury district for 50
years with his wife jan
and family.
He was a global peace activist
and he's famous and so a lot of
people are going to be weighing
in about david hart's vote
in the weeks to come.
>> he traveled to conflict
areas everywhere in the world
and did nonviolence peace
organizing.
He was raised by family
and friends who were involved
in the peace movement.
>> so this came naturally to
him and he instigated a lot of
our peace movements.
You'll find david hart so
in most peace to movements that
happened in the past 70 years,
he co-founded the nonviolent
peace force in 2002.
This sends unarmed civilian
protectors to places of
conflict in the world.
And in 2014 he co-founded world
beyond war, which is a
coalition of a dozen or more
organizations and affiliates
dedicated to peace efforts.
The wikipedia statement for
david hart's so his last name
is hrt socog h gives a brief
description of his background.
>> you can also watch youtube's
of him being interviewed about
his book waging peace and he
tells the story of his life
activism.
You can also watch a youtube
called epilog.
David and jan hart saw because
he did this was his wife as a
team and also they brought
their family along to peace
efforts.
>> if I have time I just want
to say very quickly he would
tell a story that he was
integrating lunch counters
in the south in 1960 when he
was a student someone came up
to with a knife and threatened
him and he says brother, you
can do what you.
Thank you for your comments.
Apologizes for cutting you off.
We are providing two minutes to
everyone today fellow
supervisors my name is orgill
you.
I'm a resident of district one.
I'm here today because I'm
urging this board to do a
general fund transfer to the
sfm to help prevent this year's
summer cuts.
First I'd like to say thanks
supervisors mahmood fielder
and melgar and chen for their
support on last week's rally to
prevent service cuts this
summer.
>> unfortunately the S.F. Mta
board decided to not use
reserve funds to prevent cuts
this year as a result, zero one
and five will be shortened
which will affect my ability to
get around the city.
What now is just a single
buster that's right outside my
house is now a transfer on the
15 to get to the caltrain
station which can add 15 more
minutes to my trip.
While this is still manageable
I'm concerned about muni's slow
decline as more and more
service cuts are made and kept
the two sutter the 21 hays the
58 lake said the 38 geary the
66 kintara and so much more
have all had their service cut.
Bit by bit muni is being
chipped away and becoming less
and less viable for san
franciscans and people across
the bay area.
I are just bored to stop the
bleeding and that is hurting
the over 450,000 weekday riders
.
Now's the time when the deficit
is still manageable to
administer self-help.
Let us keep the trust of
riders.
Will they still use muni so
that we can at least have our
best chance to win a ballot
measure the coming years?
>> please work with S.F. Mta on
a general fund transfer.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
My name is philip raffel.
I am a resident of district
eight.
I'm calling on board of
supervisors to prevent a
downward spiral of muni's
infrastructure and service to
the city.
And to do that please transfer
funds for the general from the
general fund to muni.
We need a city like san
francisco can't exist at its
best when its public
transportation is decrepit
and when it's limited.
If we don't if we do not act on
this when when we can manage
excuse me when we can manage
the our fire our finances we
will be at the mercy of events
beyond our control.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
Excuse me.
Good afternoon, PRESIDENT.
MR. PRESIDENT and supervisors.
My name is dorothy peterson
and I am a resident of district
ten.
I came today to ask supervisor
walton who is not here today to
have a hearing on some of the
injustices going on with age
related and regency.
In other words, we're having a
rehabilitation going on.
I am a part of that rehabbing
and repairing and as a part of
that rehabbing and repairing
one of the things insurance
and the contract says while my
house is under the care of
related management it is
supposed to be kept safe
and secure.
>> while I was gone and my
house under related under the
care of related at my house was
viciously vandalized and blood
put on my door.
There's a 156 units
in shoreview.
I only asked one thing why this
is a hate crime.
>> why was my unit out of 156
units viciously vandalized
inside?
>> I didn't have the key inside
and blood splattered on my door
when maintenance cleaned it the
first time they did it a second
time.
Now I would like to have a
hearing as to why I was being
targeted and why are they not
honoring.
>> why are they not honoring
the contracts that are supposed
to be signed?
Thank you.
Comments.
You know it took okay.
>> next speaker.
Hello.
My name is janice smith.
I'm also a resident of the
bayview.
Under related management which
is district ten.
And it seemed like to not get
any help from MR. Martin.
And I truly hope the borough
supervisors could step in.
I was trying to show these
pictures as west MS..
Peterson just said there they
receive my money from hood.
They received bond money.
They received money from city.
But we lady management and this
is not the first merry go round
with related this happened also
we posted our rehabilitation
done in 2021.
But a whole bunch of money came
up misty.
I'm not going to mention the
people's name.
So we never had it back in 21.
So now we have it now with
2425.
The same thing is going on
there working with this company
called regency and shamrock
movers with the movers a lot of
the people's property are being
damaged.
A lot of properties coming up
missing.
I'm not going to say stolen but
a lot of properties coming up
missing.
They're putting used doors as
front doors.
They have put a bathroom door
as our front door where you
could just put the little stick
pin in it and open it up.
And I have pictures I would
like to leave with you guys is
with the blood in the mold on
her door.
This is the door daughter.
She was giving which is not
new.
This is the mold that's still
on her balcony.
She can't even stand outside of
her apartment to look over the
railing.
>> this is the inside coming
from a house where you actually
there's a hold where mouses are
been able to climb into her
apartment.
>> these are the garages.
Yes.
Some of them they're supposed
to be new garages.
>> this is a state of an
emergency.
One here is like we're not even
being cared for is as if
they're just overlooking us up
there.
But we need help up there
in district ten and just
actually impossible via the
stairwell please come together
because since MR. Walton is not
helping us.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker griffin lee,
district two resident
and passionate san franciscan
one I wanted to urge you on the
item ahead item number 31 it
looks completely irresponsible
to be asking for $2 billion
from the governor
and california legislator.
>> it shows a lack of
accountability
and responsibility on behalf of
you board and as the mta I
deeply feel and many san
franciscans feel the same way
in a sense that you got to dig
deep within the 78 budget to
save muni.
>> I'm a I'm advocate
and positive about muni if you
start asking the state for
money now and a regional bond
measure comes up in 2026 at the
same time you're going to cut
$7.2 million of service cuts
this summer.
>> you're already after a back
start.
Do not put this on the backs of
the public.
Many of you ran on
accountability.
It's time to stick to that plan
and stick to the word and do
not disrupt the public from
more money.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's hear from our next
speaker please.
Can you.
>> hello.
Good afternoon.
Supervisors and board of oh
that just took give san
francisco my name is jovan.
I came right here today because
we're having issues in the
district of the mission on 24th
and I like we're trying to
avoid homeless people and cars
blocking the alley because
we've been having issues where
people using the restroom
in the alley where there's
restrooms and areas of the
street like by bart station
and they don't respect people
living right there in the alley
of 24th and lilac.
And we've been high incidents
of cars, motorcycles
and different kind of issues
and we were trying to avoid
incidents right there and we
need to have more patrols right
there to keep an eye on the
alley of 24th and I look to
24th and 25th for safety issues
because there's tours of
schools of the san francisco
public schools and we're trying
to avoid incidents where people
can get hurt.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome to our next speaker
>> ihis book up here as
if to please and lamech lived
182 years and begat a son
and he called his name noah
saying this same she'll comfort
us concerning our work and toil
of our hands because of the
ground which the lord is cursed
and lamech lived after he begat
noah 595 years and begat sons
and daughters and all the days
of lamech were 777 years and he
died.
>> now it's interesting this is
a patriarch very important man
lamech, the father of noah
and he is number 595.
It also pops up if we
understand jeremiah 28 verse
one part a the first 23 words
it gives us a chronology a
precise chronology from when
solomon's temple was destroyed
and herod's temple was
destroyed.
Okay, it really does.
And you won't read this in any
book but I can prove it.
It was 595 years between the
two.
It happened on the same day it
happened on the same year.
>> they were both sabbath years
.
This 595 years was 85
sabbatical cycles.
It's the same thing.
>> it is now been 200 and 85
sabbatical cycles from when
christ was anointed and when he
was anointed that's when he
started turning the world
around.
Okay, we're now in the next one
but we could still say it's
been 285 sabbatical cycles.
Christ is coming soon.
The sun is dark and think about
it aoc is saying her
constituency are the illegal
aliens aliens boasberg this is
a darkening of the sun.
He's undermining the authority
of the PRESIDENT This guy who's
got a lifetime job appointed by
somebody.
>> thank you for your comments.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
MR. PRESIDENT, MADAM Clerk what
I do duffy I want to just say
GOD please GOD bless this poor
and I don't want to become too
secular.
I don't think people realize
how deeply religious
and spiritual the community of
san francisco is although there
are many different flavors
and it's I believe it's ramadan
right now.
It's also lent.
It's also just a couple of
weeks from the 2,568th birthday
of buddha among other things
and I would mention many other
spiritual beliefs but I only
got 60s.
>> the dalai lama said there
are many, many ways many paths
to enlightenment and I think
that's right up there with the
with the golden rule likewise.
And when we talk about recovery
there there are so many
different paths to recovery
just this time I've never heard
of recovery without a higher
power.
But just today I learned that
there's such a way of a secular
way of doing it and it just
speaks to how many different
ways there are.
>> thank you.
Thank you MR. Duffy for your
comments before the next
speaker if there are any other
members of the public who'd
like to provide general public
comment these last two maybe
our last two speakers welcome.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
And board members.
My name is richard sc peterson.
I speak almost weekly.
I am a senior and I am disabled
.
>> I am also a muni rider.
I do not drive a car I cannot
see well enough to drive a car
and I ride the muni daily
and see how many people
actually use than the muni
and my drive here is one of the
most wonderful I take the
roller coaster 24 to crosstown
bus to market street and take
one of the brilliant streetcars
down market street to the board
here muni is in trouble
and about a year ago I thought
it was at its peak where the
busses were clean and the
busses were running on time.
Lately the busses have been
bunched together.
Their timing does not seem to
be well well regulated and it's
going down.
The other comment I wanted to
make was about the taxi drivers
and this relates to transport
station as well because we know
that the taxi drivers in san
francisco were well can we call
it screwed by having to buy
their their placards for
usually around $250,000 at the
hall and I think that in any
negotiations and you people
negotiate with the with the the
airport you ought to make sure
that some money is carved out
from those negotiate ations to
recompense the the actual taxi
drivers service our city.
>> thank you thank you for your
comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
Thank you.
Good afternoon board of
supervisors thank you for your
service and that includes
public comment.
I've been in your shoes
and probably attended about a
hundred public hearings as an
elected official and wanted to
come out to you because I know
of the great uncertainty that
the city and county of san
francisco is facing with what's
happening at the federal level
and a a a policy or a strategy
of lobbying and litigation is
in full proof and inevitably
tough choices will have to be
made and those choices will
have to remain through at least
JANUARY 20th, 2029 and dealing
with uncertainty and variable
revenue is difficult for
government.
You're not used to variable
revenue of such extreme that's
being proposed because we're
talking about billions of
dollars but corporations are
used to this variability.
They deal with big market
swings and they have to
forecast at 99% accuracy
and you don't have to go that
far to understand that your own
local san francisco companies
use something called modeling
what if scenarios so you all
have questions all the time
that you probably ask a
processional staff what if this
what if that and in those
situations those corporations,
those boards which are the
equivalent to the board of
supervisors have information at
their fingertips that when they
ask a what if question they can
get an answer right away
instead of waiting a long time
because city of san francisco
governments using archaic
spreadsheets and spreadsheets
are slow fallible
and unfortunately when those
people leave the city through
attrition you lose all that
information.
So you only have to go as far
as talking to google adobe
salesforce autodesk openai
databricks docusign, you name
it they're already using this
technology in the city of san
francisco to help them and I
think you don't have to
reinvent the wheel.
Just go to them, go what are
you doing to model what if
scenario use and if there's any
questions (408) 905-6384 thank
you thank you for your
comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
I wanted to say if we don't
want strangers or our neighbors
to acquire rights in our
properties and backyards san
francisco, california
and california should increase
the statutory period of adverse
possession and prescriptive
easement to ten years keeping
pace with neighboring states
discouraging social conflict
and incivility.
But I want to say that after a
long time something has
galvanized the will and the
spirit of the community the
board, the dia mayor, the city
attorney or assemblywoman
governor or governor, the
PRESIDENT, the ag and law
enforcement with respect to
building consensus on reducing
overdose fatalities through
policing investigation
interdiction, prosecution
and more rarely deportation it
is of primary importance to
address and reduce supply
addiction and demand.
Medications that break
addiction MAY be a habit
forming not easily relinquished
and require a timely withdrawal
.
I'd prefer if the board didn't
reconsider needles a former
thorn in the city's side.
The reported usage today is
less than distribution of the
needles.
It's not an issue of clean
needles or sharing dirty
needles.
It's been a matter of consumer
preference and the availability
of substitutes.
What is preferable is a general
reduction in demand altogether
representing the maximum
preferred outcome other
countries and nations
substantially overcame similar
issues.
>> are we less than other
countries?
Are we less able?
I think not.
So good work often yields
positive results through trial
and effort learning from errors
and through taking ownership
and it takes less of our time
that way.
>> thank you for your comments.
Any other members of the public
like to address the board for
general public comment?
>> all right.
Seeing none, MR. PRESIDENT.
All right.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Public comment is closed
and now let's go to our for
adoption of that committee
reference agenda items 31
through 37 items 31 through 37
were introduced for adoption
but without committee reference
a unanimous vote is required
for adoption of a resolution on
first reading today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require a resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
>> all right.
I don't see anybody severing
any of the items.
So MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll right on items 31
through 37 supervisor cheryl
cheryl eyes supervisor chan
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor dorsey dorsey
eyes supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin mandolin I
and supervisor melgar I melgar
I there are nine eyes.
>> then without objection the
resolutions are adopted and the
motions are approved and MADAM
Clerk do we have any imperative
agenda items?
>> I have no imperatives to
report.
>> then could you please read
the in memoriam?
Yes is today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of supervisor dorsey
for the late MR. Seriously T.C.
Coats the second on behalf of
supervisor fielder for the late
MR. Curtis kimball and on
behalf of supervisor melgar for
the late justice timothy
aloysius wishes reardon thank
you, MADAM Clerk.
I believe that brings us to the
end of our agenda do we have
any further business before us
today?
>> that concludes our business
for today.
>> then we are adjourned